<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Short history of the kings of England shewing, what right every king had to the crown, and the manner of their wearing of it, especially from William the Conqueror, to James the Second, that abdicated his three kingdoms : wherein is made appear there hath been no direct succession in the line to create an hereditary right, for six or seven hundred years / faithfully collected out of our best histories.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60080</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24562658</idno>
  <idno type="VID">109707</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264174010</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3601</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42224</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">24562658</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60080)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109707)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1709:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Short history of the kings of England shewing, what right every king had to the crown, and the manner of their wearing of it, especially from William the Conqueror, to James the Second, that abdicated his three kingdoms : wherein is made appear there hath been no direct succession in the line to create an hereditary right, for six or seven hundred years / faithfully collected out of our best histories.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109707:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109707:1"/>
            <p>A Short HISTORY OF THE Kings of England: SHEWING, What Right every King had to the Crown, and the manner of their wearing of it, especially from <hi>WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM</hi> the Conqueror, to <hi>JAMES</hi> the Second, that Abdicated his Three Kingdoms▪</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is made appear there hath been no direct Succession in the Line to create an Hereditary Right, for Six or Seven Hundred years. Faithfully Collected out of our best Histories.</p>
            <q>Nihil est Imperium ut Sapientes definiunt, nisi cura salutis alienae,<bibl>
                  <hi>Amianus.</hi> Lib. 9.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, London,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109707:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109707:2"/>
            <head>THE True Portraiture of the Kings of <hi>ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND,</hi> drawn from their Titles, Successions, Reigns and Ends, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TO treat of the Nature and Difference of Governments, the distinction and preheminence of Monarchy, or Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stocracy, with the other kinds and forms, which have, according to the temper of the People, and the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of providence, had their course in the World, will be useless in this discourse, which is calculated only for his Nation, and to describe not so much the Government, as the Persons who have ruled among us, and is only suited to Monarchy as it hath had the sway of the English Throne; a Discourse not so plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing as profitable; we are loth to have our old Soars launced, or to think of change, though it be of misery, the temper of this Nation being apt to be pleased with any thing that is stately and costly, though never so dangerous and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; yet something must be said in General, to prepare the way for the particulars of this Treatise, which is not intended as controversal, or definitive of the Nature of things, but meerly practical and demonstrative, fit for every Eye that means not to shut himself up in blindness, and darkness.</p>
            <p>As the Foundation and Original of Government is confest to be of equal Antiquity with the Generation and Multiplication of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: so doubtless the just and Methodical use, and due management of it, is as necessary to the well being of men, as the exact propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and orderly motions of the Heavens are to the preservation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109707:3"/> of the Globes; and certainly without it the rational World would be more miserable then the material without Sun Moon and Stars, with all coelestial influences, which as they do beautifie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spangle the World, so they do preserve it from returning to its first Chaos and rude Mass of matter; nothing being more contrary to that unity and harmony, which the God of Nature hath moulded and disposed all things at first in, then disorder and confusion, in which, as there is nothing of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dditys to be discerned, so nothing of peace or happiness can possibly be found.</p>
            <p>And notwithstanding all this, the World hath scarce known what the Natural sweetness and true benefits of Government are, but only as comparative and rather as opposite to Anarchy, then as advancing really and effectually the just Liberties and Freedoms of Societies, or propagating the Commonwealth of mankind; for what through the ignorance and sloath of the people and the Pride and Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Governors, the whole order and end of Government hath been inverted and subverted, upon all occasions, and that which was made for the good of the whole, hath been so contracted, and circumscribed in one person, that the great and Soveraign us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and end of it, by practise and custom, hath been rather to set up the pomp and state of one man, and his Family, then to promote or propagate the profit and happiness of the Universe; and whereas of right to its constitution, it should have a free Election as its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal and common good for its end, and just and equal Laws for its rule, it hath had usurpation for its Principle, and Tyranny and Bondage for its medium and end. As to this day we may see in the greatest part of the World, where all the Liberties of Millions of men of all sorts of conditions and ranks, are buryed in the Glory and splendor of one Family; through which narrow Channels, all Honour and justice, all Law and reason are to run up and down the World.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Goodness and Beauty of Government consists in the Harmonious Temperature of power and obedience of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Liberty, it hath been quite otherwise inverted by practise, and made apparent to lie in the Majesty and Greatness of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, and the absolute Subjection and servitude of the people; and the excellency and sweetness of it rather to be seen in the presence Chamber, and the mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ificence and Grandeur of the Court, then in the Courts of Justice and the rich and flourishing Estate of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109707:3"/> Kingdom, nothing being accounted more political, and glorious' then to have the Prince high, and the Subjects Beggers; and yet this Ceremonial way of Government, hath took most place in the World, and got almost divine adoration, and hath thrust out all other forms of Government, equally sacred with it self, and most proportionable to the Nature and benefits of societies, and the Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simple of all the Liberties of the people (which are as their Blood and Spirits in their Veins) sold to maintain its State.</p>
            <p>Besides many causes and grounds of this degeneration (whereby so much misery hath overflowed the Nations of the World) I find two, which at present are principally to be mentioned; the first is the neglect of a right Sence, and the often inculcating the original and end of Government; and the next a lineal succession or continuation of Government, by a Natural and supposed heirship; For want of the first, neither the people know their own rights, or how to maintain them; or the Governor his use and end, nor how to keep himself within the just bounds and limits of his Creation; for what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the stupidity and ignorance of the people in not knowing their primitive priviledges, that they are the original and end of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and the pride and ambition of men, when once they have got power, forget both how they came by it, and to what end they are distinguished from other men, Government comes both to be Usurped and Tyrannical Did the people but know that their Choice and Election is the foundation of just Authority and that none can rule over them but whom they appoint, they would not then be drawn into controversies and debates, whether it be Treason in them to cast off a bad Governor, who have the only power of choosing a good one; and on the other side, if Kings and Princes (for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all to them who have been most guilty of the abuse of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) had but the continual Sence of the root from whence they sprung, and the duties annexed to their Offices, they could not look on themselves as Rulers, but Tyrants, when they acted for their own private Prerogative, in distinction from, and contrary to, the Liberties and Freedoms of the people; but these considerations have been by time and prescription worn out of the mind and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of both, partly through continual insinuations of Court Maxims, and the Spirit of Bondage in the people, and by force and usurpation in the Magistrate, whereby it hath gone a long while for currant, that the people have no power, nor the Prince no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109707:4"/> to give but to God, from whom they challenge an immediate title, as if Kings and Princes, all their names and successions were let down from Heaven, in the same sheet that the Beasts were in <hi>Peters</hi> vision, and had no their root in the Earth as all other Magistrates besides. We have had much ado of late, to beat off from these Royal notions both by pens and swords, and yet still they have too strong a hold in most mens hearts, though to their own undoing.</p>
            <p>Whereas all men are equally born free, and naturaliz'd into all the priviledges of Freedom and just Liberty, no man can obtain a special power over any, but either <hi>ex pacto aut scelere,</hi> either by willing agreement and consent, which is the right and just way of title, and most natural, or by conquest and usurpation, which is most exotick and unjust; for the Original of Kingly power, in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we all know it came in as an effect of the wantonness and discontents of the <hi>Israelites,</hi> against that special way of Government God himself had set over them; And view the Character God gives to them of that Government, and not a blessing he gives them with it; for its rise among the Heathens and Nations (which knew not God among whom that Government most prevail'd; it was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly first good, and grounded on the exorbitancies and excess of other Magistrates, and a high opinion of the justice and vertue of some particular persons, as <hi>Cicero lib. offic.</hi> 2 excellently expresseth it; <hi>Mihi quidem non apud Medos solum (ut ait Herodotus) sed etiam apud majores nostros, servandae justitiae causa videntur olim bene morati Reges constituti: nam cum premeretur initio multitudo ab iis qui majores opes habebant, ad unum aliquem confugiebant virtute praestantem.</hi> As if taking it for granted that among all Nations that preservation and execution of justice, with injoyning of vertue, was the first ground of the constitution of Kings; But they having got by their own goodness chief Power and Authority, use that favour they had gained from their own deserts, to advance their own family, and having got in the affections of the people, through the sence of their own present worth, what by power and force, and what by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy and craft, got the same power entailed on their heirs, and so by custom have made succession the only right, or at least the most just to Crowns and Scepters.</p>
            <p>A principle which hath more hindred the advance of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and run it on more hazards and mischiefs then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where by a fatal Custom, people must be irreparably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109707:4"/> with what they can find, and reducing all to a blind Fate and Fortune, be he good, or prove bad <hi>talis, qualis,</hi> give up both their own Wills and Liberties to such a succession, not only by a natural necessity, but a divine institution: How the world came to be so blinded, as thus to give away their Rights and Liberties, and mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage their understandings and freedom, as bankrupts do their lands, is not to be determined, but by supposal of a Judgement of God, and an over-reach of power and force, or by an <hi>Ignis fatutis</hi> of Policy and Subtilty.</p>
            <p>For this natural and hereditary succession (which is now adored as the grand title) if truly considered, is nothing else but a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of conquest, or a surprisal by the good nature of the people, when they have been either low, and in fear, and taking advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their high esteem of some eminent person, who hath been more then ordinary instrumental to them, have got the people to convey the same honour to their posterity after them; the peoples consent being thus ravished from them, its made a Law, both civil and divine to after generations; but the world is now, or should be, grown wise: Let us consider the nature and use of this succession, both in general and particular, especially as it hath been acted in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among all the Catalogue of vanities which <hi>Solomon</hi> reckons up in his sacred retractions, there is none he puts such a character on, as for a man to spend his time and strength in getting of riches, and knows no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who shall succeed him in the enjoyment of the profit and good of his labour, or whether he may be a wise man or a fool; But what a misery, and worse than vanity is this, that the supream power of Government (in the right execution of which all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of millions of men are interessed) should be entailed on one Man (though never so deserving in his own Person) and the heirs of his body, be he good or bad, a wise man, or very nigh a fool, and so all their happiness depend on hap and hazard from ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to generation?</p>
            <p>It cannot be rationally or spiritually supposed, that any man should be born a Magistrate or Governor, especially not successively, when the best men, and most choise spirits, who have had the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Eminencies of Vertue, and best Improvement of Education and natural Genius, are hardly fit for so great a Work. If Kings have such a <hi>vis formativa</hi> in their loyns, as to beget Kings in the likeness
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109707:5"/> of their Office, as children in the image of their natures, it must be necessariy supposed, that they must generate all these Royal quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications together with them, and by the same natural necessity trans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er all their princely endowments to them also.</p>
            <p>Whereas I had almost affirmed it, (and I hope no man can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it either Heresie or Treason) that God himself cannot intail on any particular line of mankind, the Power and Authority of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment out of his wisdom and love to their happiness (without he meant to do it in judgement, and to plague the World) and not give them suitable and successive qualifications also, fit for that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; It being Gods use (according to his wisdom and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness) neither ordinarily nor extraordinarily to call out per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to any place, but he anoints them with proportionable gifts to it.</p>
            <p>And yet the poor people (whom God hath naturally made free, and to make use of their own understandings and affections for their own good) are by this succession, bound up from the improvement either of Soul or Body, fain to be content with what they can get for the present, and to shift it out from age to age (with the loss of all opportunities of choice) only with what corrupt Nature brings them forth, which oftentimes travels sorely in pain with the curse of the Fathers who begat these Governors. Hence also it comes to pass, that oftentimes Children are made Kings, and though they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable at present for the actual exercise of that office, yet are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, as having the right and title, and all things acted in their name, and the whole Commonwealth, it may be of many Nations must wait for his capacity with fear and hope, which capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city is also at best to be judged by his years, rather then fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness or qualification for so high a trust; and in the mean while the Kingdom must be governed by some Favorites of the last King, or some next kinsman to this; and while the King is thus in pupillage, we may well ask, who governs the Kingdom? And yet oftentimes it hath faln out, that their Government hath been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ordered in their nonage by others, then in their own by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, as appears especially in the raign of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and <hi>Henry</hi> the sixth, Kings of <hi>England;</hi> the first being but nine years old when his father died, the latter but nine Months; who while they were young, and under the protection of wise and sober men, the Laws were administred uprightly, and with much Justice; but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109707:5"/> when they themselves came to the years of Kingship and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, so Royalled, that both Law and Liberties were soon altered and abolished, as anon the Reader shall have a more exact account; And how sad is it, that when Government may be advanced as well, if not better by others in their minority, without their presence or influence, the world must be at such vast charges for a title, and to maintain it ere they can use it, and which is worst, that when they come to exercise it themselves, should make their title the ground of their Tyranny. But if it so happen (for its a meer chance) that the next Heir prove somewhat more then ordinary capable, yet what the next may prove, who knows? If he be an Infant, (as it many times falls out) then there must be patient and hopeful Waitings, to see what he will be when grown up; until that, there can be no further progress made in the alteration or Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Affairs, though of never so great, and present concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and when he comes to these Years, which Custom pronounceth him capable, how unreasonable is it, that nothing can hinder, or exclude him from his Authority, but that he is incapable of being begg'd for a Fool? It being enough, if he can know his own Name, and be able to write himself <hi>Rex,</hi> though he knows little what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Office, or Relation of a King.</p>
            <p>If he be one of Riper Years and Statute, on which this Succession falls, then must all the Observation of his Nature, and the omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and more than Astrological Aspects of his Constitution and Education be forgotten; and although silenced in his Pretended Title, and a full compliance looked after, though opprest with never so many fears, and secret wishes of a more hopeful Governor; yea, and though he hath been never so active against the liberties of the people, when but a Prince, and given demonstrations what a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor they may expect, yet his succession must be his qualification and indemnity, and his Title his vertue.</p>
            <p>On this ground also it comes to pass, that oftentimes women come to hold the Reigns of Government, and to steer at the Helm, as well as men; for if there be any defect of the male line, the female suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds; and that feeble and weaker sex, whom God and nature have or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to be only particular helps and good Subjects, (only to keep up the name of a Family) must be invested with the highest authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, over the choisest, and most select spirits of many Nations, and all further thoughts of bettering the State of things utterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish'd by a female pretence.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109707:6"/>
            <p>And which is most desperate by this succession, and its plea of the only and absolute right) the Fundamental liberties of the people are not only insensibly undermined, but absolutly rooted up, and that Birth-right, Priviledge of the people, their Election and Choice, then which they have nothing more natural, and which is far more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary to them and theirs, then by all the Laws of God, nature and reason Crowns can be to Kings and their heirs, is quite extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished; For pass by the first King, (who it may be as with us it hath been came in by Conquest) you must go back in some King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms five hundred, in others a thousand years, ere you can but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the clear notion of a free Election (wherein the people's power and priviledge is alone and peculiarly seen) and yet that so faintly and hardly extorted from them, as great loans of money from a cruel miser, without use or advantage; and though Election must be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged at last, the first just ground of Government, yet custom in successions soon wears out its right, and transfers it on the next Blood; And though in <hi>England</hi> it appears by the Coronation Oath, that there is even in succession a kind of Election, yet its so limited in the line, that its as good as nothing, and so weak and implicitly manifested, that its but meer customary Ceremony, which always is pursued by the natural title, and only used to deceive the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and as a step to the further confirmation of a more Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental and sure right; and its easie to demonstrate it; for our Kings soon forget it, ere they come from <hi>Westminister</hi> to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> or from the Chair of Inauguration to the Presence Chamber. In a word, what gives all this ground of such an inevitable and successively insensible incroachment on the Laws and Liberties of Nations, but this lineal title, whereby the Son without remedy goes on where the Father left off, and by a divine pretence seiseth on what by nature is due to the meanest Subject, as to himself? And what makes the present Kings so daring, and venturous to raise their own Prerogative, but this that they know there can be no alienation of the Crown from his Heirs, and that they may make it better (that is more Tyrannical?) but surer they cannot: And thus there is a constant hope and possibility, by continuation and propagation of principles and designs, backed with Title and Authority, that what cannot be done in one Kings reign, may be done in the next, and so on; For the minds of Princes are not u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually contracted, or contented with present enjoyments; especially
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109707:6"/> if there be any restraint on their wills, or more of height, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to be attained unto.</p>
            <p>Yea, this is one of the main reasons (that in our times can be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred) why we have had such uneven actings, and such strange alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in several Kings Raigns; the principles, and Laws; the people have been always the same, who are capable of small or no variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or change, but as higher, and supream influences move them, of which none hath been so powerful as Princes, who as they are Stars of the first magnitude, so of the strongest operations; and though the people be compared to the Sea, yet as the Sea, they have no turbulent motion of their own, but what is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned by violent and uncertain winds; but the great change hath been by the temper and actings of Princes, and commonly the next successor hath been the omen and fate of the times; if any way good, then the Nation smiled, and his raign began the Spring; if probable, there was hopes; and yet both these at first promised, but at length frustrated; and however the beginnings were, yet the succession of acts demonstrated how the Title was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for until they have made their succession sure, none have been more fair, and promising; but afterwards both Laws and Liberties, like favourites, have been advanced <hi>ad placitum;</hi> and what they have got an interest in by nature, that by Prerogative they have centred in their own proper persons, even the most fundamental privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the people, and have only granted Leases unto the people of their own inheritances, and dated them not for life (which would have been too great a mercy) but as long as the Royal pleasure lasts, which changes always with advantages. Yea, by this succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion Tyranny is so intailed, and all things so necessarily acted, as if the Prince were not only the civil, but natural Parent of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that Kings had begot the people as so many Bastards to obey, as they do beget one lawfully to raign over them.</p>
            <p>Its too well known, that good and wise men are the fewest of the Sons of men, and are commonly pickt out here and there, as rich Pearls on the shoar of violent torrents; but to expect in one Line and Family, a succession of good, wise and governing men is almost as probable to Christians, as to expect Mahomets second coming among the <hi>Turks,</hi> after so many hundred years delusion; and although it must be acknowledged, that there have been some good Kings, yet they have been so few, that as their names
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109707:7"/> from the beginning of the World can hardly make up the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Letters in the Almanack, or possibly supply the Holy days in the year, so a little goodness hath gone far, and at the best we shall find it but comparative; good Kings instead of better Governors, as some of the <hi>Roman Caesurs,</hi> chose these to succed them who were worse than themselves, that they might commend, and set off their own Reign, though tyrannical enough in it self; and we may without any passion demonstrate, that the design by Succession hath been rather to keep up the Governors, and palliate their vices, than ever to maintain or heighten the glory and splendor, or carry on the benefit of the Government it self in the execution of good and righteous Laws.</p>
            <p>But to come nigher home, and leave generals (granting Succession in it self to be a good Title let us view without partiality, the succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> whereby they plead their Title to the Crown, and we shall find in our Histories, that nothing hath been more commonly interrupted, than a Succession of the next Heir, and for this seven or eight hundred years (if not more) we have not had succession continued in any even line or justright, and no Title was ever more broken and unjust than of our Kings, if they make a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal and Hereditary succession the foundation of their right; Let us look but a little back to those which preceeded the <hi>Norman</hi> race, especially among the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> the ancient competitors for the Government of this Nation, and it will appear, that the right Heir hath been commonly past by; and Strangers or Usurpers preferred; to go no further back then to <hi>Alfred</hi> King of the West <hi>Saxons,</hi> and the twenty fourth Monarch of the <hi>English</hi> Men; as soon as he died, <hi>Athlestan</hi> his Bastard was preferred before his legitimate Son <hi>Edmond,</hi> and after him got his own Brother <hi>Edmond</hi> to succeed him (<hi>Dan. Hist.</hi> p. 14. <hi>Speed.</hi>) and though this <hi>Edmond</hi> left two Sons, <hi>Edwin,</hi> and <hi>Edgar,</hi> yet as he and his former Brother had Usurped the Government, so <hi>Edred</hi> his Brother stept into the Throne, and put them by until he had finished his Reign, and then they took their turns; <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> first, and <hi>Edgar</hi> after him; this <hi>Edgar</hi> had two Wives, <hi>Ethelsled</hi> his First, and <hi>Elfrida</hi> the Second: by the first he had issue, <hi>Edward,</hi> Sir-named the Martyr, who succeeded his Father in Title; but having hardly felt the Crown warm, and fast on his Head, was cruelly Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, to make way for the second Wives Son <hi>Ethelred</hi> who suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him, as <hi>Daniel</hi> well expresseth it, whose entrance into his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109707:7"/> Reign was Blood, the middle Misety, and the end Confusion; and though he left his Son <hi>Edmond,</hi> Sir named <hi>Ironside,</hi> to succeed him, yet <hi>Canntus</hi> the <hi>Dane</hi> by compact got half of the Kingdom from him, and soon after the whole, setting up his <hi>Danish</hi> Title, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the two Sons <hi>Edmond</hi> had left, with his Brother <hi>Edwin,</hi> that no further pretence might be made by them of their Title; and now come the <hi>Danes</hi> to convey their Title by <hi>Canatus;</hi> and yet <hi>Harold</hi> his Bastard gets the Crown before <hi>Hardicanute,</hi> who was his legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Son; and among these three Kings (for the Government under the <hi>Danes</hi> continued but twenty six years;) and only under these three was none Usurper, &amp; immediately interrupted the right of succession. And the <hi>Danes</hi> Government being ended, (which was but an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of conquest) the <hi>Saxons</hi> regain their Title; and <hi>Edward,</hi> called the <hi>Confessor,</hi> the seventh Son of <hi>Elthelred</hi> (who came in with the Murther of the right Heir) being kept as a reserve in <hi>Normandy</hi>) is Elected King, and the <hi>Saxons</hi> Title now begins to revive, but soon it is extinguished, not only by the <hi>Norman</hi> pretence, but by the next successor, <hi>Harold</hi> the Second, Son to <hi>Goodwin,</hi> Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> who came in with the expulsion of <hi>Edgar Athlings</hi> the proper suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor (<hi>Vide Speed.</hi>)</p>
            <p>And with <hi>Harold</hi> ended the <hi>Saxon</hi> race, which had lasted about five hundred years, after the coming in of <hi>Hengist,</hi> and their Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this Kingdom; and yet you see what have been the Titles suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively of these former Kings, wherein the Line hath not only been now and then through force and violence cut off and discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, but usurpation solemnized with as much Ceremony as any natural pretence: but these Instance are but as representations of objects afar off, which may seem otherwise then they are; we will go on and review the Title of our Kings from <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Norman,</hi> Sir-named the Conqueror, and by whom, not only the line, but all the whole frame of Laws and Liberties were not only curtail'd but changed, for though in the Reigns of the former Kings, every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror made his impression, and drew his Picture in <hi>England,</hi> yet never was the whole Scene of State changed until now, and a new Model so peremptorily (and without repeal) introduced, as by him: The first <hi>jus,</hi> or right of his Title (the only foundation of all the rest of our latter Kings) we all know was by meer Conquest, which as it is a disseisin in Law, so an unjust Title in Reason, and common to one as unto another: yet he thought a Bastard, (and so
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109707:8"/> had less Title to his Dukedom then to <hi>England</hi> which he won by the Sword) made himself the principal of that divine Succession we now stand upon, and all our Kings have no other pretence then by the succession of his Sword; and certainly, if the Fountain, and Head-Spring be corrupt, the stream cannot be Christial and pure; and yet (as Baron <hi>Thorpe</hi> declares in his Charge given at the Assizes holden at <hi>York</hi> the twentieth of <hi>March,</hi> 1648 and now in Print) of all these twenty four <hi>Kings,</hi> which have <hi>King'd</hi> it amongst us since that <hi>William,</hi> there are but seven of them that could pretend legali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to succeed their former (predecessors, either by lineal, or collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Title, and he might have contracted that number, (and have been modest enough.) But that the Reader may not be prejudiced, or wrap up his understanding in any expression, let him but follow the descents of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in the line, (and pardon the first strange and exortick way of right) and he will discover, that as the first Title was created by force, so the succession hath been continued by usurpation. <hi>Speed</hi> (too Royal a Writer) gives us a hint to go on upon in the Life of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, page 746 (asketh by way of Interrogation) What right had <hi>Will</hi> the Conqueror, the Father of all our glorious Tyrants? What right (we speak, saith he, of a right of equity) had his Son <hi>William Rufus,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the first, while their Elder Brother lived? and so he goes on. But to give a more particular account to the Reader, how every <hi>King</hi> came to his Crown, let us begin with the first of the first.</p>
            <p>After that the first <hi>William,</hi> who laid the foundation of his right in the Blood of the <hi>English,</hi> had left this World, as well as his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, great strivings there were who should succeed; and though he left three Sons, <hi>Robert, William</hi> and <hi>Henry,</hi> yet could leave but one Heir, which was <hi>Robert;</hi> yet <hi>William</hi> Sir-named <hi>Rufus,</hi> gets the Crown set on his head, notwithstanding the elder brothers title, and though <hi>Robert</hi> fights for his right, yet being too weak in the field, is forc't to a composition, on these terms that he should injoy it after his decease, if he hapned to survive; and yet notwithstanding, <hi>Henry</hi> the youngest Brother (called <hi>Henry</hi> the First) steps in, and makes use of his Brothers absence to set up himself in his place; and <hi>Robert</hi> yet surviving, he wears it in his stead; and however he strove to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his right, he at last was fain to yield up, not only his Title, but his Person to <hi>Henry,</hi> who not only unjustly excluded him from the succession to the Kingdom, but cruelly put out his Eyes that he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109707:8"/> might only feel his misery, and never see his remedy. The line male of the Conqueror is now extinct, as well as it was irregularly diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; as <hi>William</hi> got his right by his Sword, so all his successors main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it in imitation of him, rather then by any legal pretence they could derive from him. But <hi>Henry</hi> the first (though he had come in over the back of his Elder Brother) that he might make more sure work for a succession, wanting issue male living, pitcheth on <hi>Maud</hi> his Daughter, formerly married to the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, who left her a Widow, and died without issue; and having sworn all the Nobility (especially <hi>Stephen</hi>) to her, ordained her and her issue to be his successors in <hi>Englands</hi> Throne, and married her again to <hi>Jeoffrey Plantagenet,</hi> the Son and her Heir apparent of <hi>Fulk,</hi> then Earl of <hi>Anjou,</hi> by whom she had three Sons, <hi>Henry, Jeffrey,</hi> and <hi>William;</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> the Crown belonged as next Heir af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Mother (by the usurped Title of his Father,) yet <hi>Stephen,</hi> Earl of <hi>Mortain,</hi> and <hi>Bulleign,</hi> Son to <hi>Adelincia</hi> the third Daughter of <hi>Willaim</hi> the Conqueror, by <hi>Maud</hi> his wife, (notwithstanding his Oath to the last King) gets the Crown set on his own head, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes her, and her issue for the present; yet after he died, <hi>Henry,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the second, Sirnamed <hi>Shortmantle,</hi> though his Mother was alive, enjoys it. This <hi>Henry</hi> had six Sons, <hi>William, Henry Richard, Jeoffrey, Philip, John;</hi> the two first dying, <hi>Richard</hi> the third Son, the first of that name, Sirnamed <hi>Ceur de Lyon</hi> succeeded his Father; this <hi>Richard</hi> dying without issue, his youngest Brother <hi>John</hi> usurps the Crown, notwithstanding <hi>Jeoffrey</hi> his Eldest Brother had left a young Son, named <hi>Arthur Plantaganet King</hi> of <hi>Brittain,</hi> who was Heir appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the Crown; and after he dyed, <hi>Henry</hi> his Son the third of that name succeeds him, though <hi>Arthurs</hi> Sister was then alive, (though in prison) who was next to the Title (such as it was) after him <hi>Edward</hi> Sirnamed <hi>Longshanks,</hi> called <hi>Edward</hi> the first, lays hold on the Crown and wore it with much Majesty, and after him <hi>Edward</hi> the second his Son goes on, but still on the old account, and on the ruin of the most proper Heirs; this <hi>Edward</hi> was deposed by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his ill Government, as anon shall be more fully related; and his Son <hi>Edward</hi> the third of that name set up in his room; after him followed <hi>Richard</hi> the second, Son to the black Prince, who was also deposed, after whose dethroning, <hi>Henry</hi> called the fourth, Son to <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and Uncle to the former King, snatcheth up the Crown, though of right it was to descend to <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Mortimore,</hi> Earl of <hi>March,</hi> the Son and Heir of <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109707:9"/> of <hi>Clarence,</hi> the third Son of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and an Elder Brother of <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaster;</hi> and thus we have nothing hitherto, but interruption and usurpation; and those which in their own reigns can pretend a Divine Title by succession, which must not be altered, can for their advantage put by the succession of the issue of others. But to go on, Here now began the Bloody Wars and Contests be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the House of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> which made the World to ring of the misery of the Civil Wars of <hi>England,</hi> and all about a Title, and neither of them (if seriously weighed) had a right Title by succession, if the first Title of their Ancestors were to be the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal; But that custom might be the best right, he got in his Son <hi>Henry,</hi> who was the fifth of that name, to succeed; and his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the sixth (though an infant) takes his place, until <hi>Edward</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> overthrew his Army in the Battel at <hi>Towton</hi> Field, and got him deposed, and was Proclaimed King by the name of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, though the Title had been carried on in the House of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster</hi> thorow three descents; thus favor and fortune, not lineal suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession always gave the best Title; this <hi>Edward</hi> left two Sons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, (to maintain the succession of the House of <hi>York) Edward</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> and five Daughters. His Eldest Son <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> who was the fifth of that name, succeeded him in Claim and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but rather lived then raigned (being an infant) had never any actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al exercise of his Government; for <hi>Ric.</hi> Duke of <hi>Glocster,</hi> and Uncle to this Infant and made his Protector, that he might set up himself, causeth both the young Titular King and his Brother, (these two Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Infants) to be barbarously Murthered in their Beds, and so wears the Crown himself, by the name of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, until <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Richmond</hi> (a twig of a Bastard of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi>) by his valour at <hi>Bosworth</hi> field having overthrown his Army, slew the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant himself and created by his sword (for other he had none) a new Title to himself, and was Crowned King, by the name of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, who, what by his power and by a marriage of the Lady <hi>Eliz.</hi> the Eldest Daughter of <hi>Ed.</hi> the Fourth confirmed his succession, and from him do all our later Princes derive their Title, as <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, <hi>Queen Mary, Queen Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> King <hi>Charles,</hi> I. &amp;c. This <hi>Henry,</hi> the foundation of our great ones, was himself but a private man, who as <hi>Speed</hi> says, had scarce any thing of a just Title, or of a warrantable intention but to remove an Usurper; besides there were many natural Heirs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109707:9"/> of the House of <hi>York,</hi> which were Children of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence Richards</hi> Elder Brother, who had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter right, but when once a Title is made, it must be maintained, and if it can but get throw two or three Successors, it's presently Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed to be <hi>jure divino,</hi> and pleaded as the only just Title and Right.</p>
            <p>Thus you have a faithful and true account of the succession of our <hi>Norman Monarchs;</hi> we can only say we have had so many persons raigning, and as Kings of <hi>England;</hi> but for a Title by lineal succession, there is none, but what every man may make as well as any man, and what is as proper to a stranger, as to an Heir; power, and favour, murther and deceit being the most common principles of the right of most of our Kings to their Government over us. If it be asked, as <hi>Speed</hi> doth, what right had <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror? then it must follow, what right had all the rest? but supposing his right, what right had these, who so many times cut off the line, and made themselves the Stock of future succession? and what mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery is it that this broken and usurped Title must still be forced on us, even by an Ecclesiastical and Divine Institution, who have now a way of redeeming our Liberties, and bettering our conditions, and following the direct line of just and true Titles, the Election and choice of the people? Is not five or six hundred years enough for <hi>England</hi> to be under the succession of a <hi>Norman</hi> Bastard (pardon the expression, its true though plain) and to be sold with all its li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, from usurpation to usurpation, as well as from generation to generation? I need not be very zealous in application, the History is enough to make all wise men consider, by whom we have all this while been governed, and upon what terms; How Tyranny and usurpation comes to be adored, if it have but a Royal name added to it. Shall the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> be now blamed for cutting off Usurpers and Tyrants, and reducing affairs to their first natural and right principle; or will the people of <hi>England</hi> after all their experiences, centre their Liberties and Freedoms in a customary usurpation of succession, and lose their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth for the personal Glory of a Pretender? especially, when they have fought against the Father, and cut him off as a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, endeavour to set up the Son to follow on both the first cause, and revenge, meerly because he was supposed to be proceeded of his loyns: this blindness will be our misery, and endear us
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109707:10"/> to a more perfect and more Tyrannical slavery then ever yet <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> felt.</p>
            <p>But to go on, the Reader hath seen what a line we have had in <hi>England,</hi> and how pure a Title our Kings have had to their Crowns; Lets now but have patience to view their actings successively, and yet shortly, and we shall better guess of their right by their raigns; for though one would think that they should endeavour to make good a bad Title by a good raign, yet it hath been far otherwise; every man having made his right by force, maintained it by Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and when they have gotten power, never remembered how, or to what end they attained it; if we look back again, and make a new and strict survey of their several actings in their Government, and go over every Kings head since <hi>Willam</hi> the Conqueror, we shall not much mistake if we pass by <hi>Turky, Russia,</hi> the <hi>Moors,</hi> and yet call <hi>Englands</hi> Kings Tyrants, and their Subjects Slaves; and however in the Theory and System it have been limited and bounded by good and distinguishing Laws, yet in the exercise an practic part almost of every <hi>King's</hi> Raign we shall find it deserve as bad a name as others who are called most absolute; for the Laws and Priviledges which this poor Nation hath enjoyed, as they have been but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementally granted for the most part, and with much design, so they have ever (upon any occasion) proved but weak and low Hedges against the Spring-tides, and Land-floods of the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Prince, which hath always gained more on the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the people, then ever the Sea by all its washing and beatings of its boysterous and unmerciful Waves hath gained on the Land; for if, at any time the poor Commons (through much strugling, and a good and present necessitous mood of the Prince) have got off any present oppressions, and forced out the promise for enacting of any good and seasonable Laws: yet either the next advantage, or at least the next successor, hath been sure, either to silence, or disannul it, and incroached upon it; and never was Priviledge or good Laws enacted, or gained to the people, but by hard pressure of the Subject, and with a predominant ingredient of the <hi>Kings</hi> advantage, and still rather out of courtesie then right. We shall find also that <hi>England</hi> for three or four hundred years together (some <hi>lucida intervalla</hi> excepted) hath been a stage of Blood, and the astonishment of all Nations in civil Wars, and that meerly, either for the clearing of the Title of the Crown
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109707:10"/> (which yet at last was only made lawful by the prevailing power, and as soon made illegal when another side got the better) or else by the Subjects and Barons, taking up Arms to defend themselves, and make Rampiers (if possible) against the inundation of Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and rather preserving, then obtaining any additions of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and yet they were commonly defeated at last; for if for the present by some eminent advantage, they got a little ground, they soon lost it again by royal stratagems, and were either forced, or complemented into their old miseries, with a worse remembrance of former actings, But to enter into the particulars of this sad Story.</p>
            <p>All men know (or may) the tyrannical domination of that First <hi>William</hi> who behaved himself as a Conqueror indeed, and a most perfect tyrant (since whom we have never had an <hi>English</hi> Man, but one, who hath been naturalized by the succession of his Conquest as King of <hi>England</hi>) he presently changed most of our Laws, especially those wherein the <hi>English</hi> liberties were most transparent, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served; and made new Laws, and those which he left, writ them all in <hi>French;</hi> disweaponed all the Natives, sent the children of the best and most faithful of the Nobility into <hi>Normandy</hi> as Hostages, and the most gallant of the <hi>English</hi> were transported by him into <hi>France</hi> to serve his Wars, that he might extinguish their Families; he advanced his <hi>Normans</hi> into all places of the Nation, and kept them as a guard over the <hi>English;</hi> brought in the Cruel Forrest Laws, and dispeopled for thirty miles together in <hi>Hampshire,</hi> pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down many Towns and Villages, with Churches, Chappels, and Gentlemens Houses, making it a Forrest for wild Beasts, (which is ever since named the <hi>New Forrest,</hi> but was the old ensign of our misery and slavery) he laid on innumerable Taxes, and made Laws royal, very severe, and in an unknown Language, that the <hi>English</hi> offending might forfeit their Estates and Lands to him, which they often did, through ignorance: But alas, what need I mention these? who ever reads but our Histories (and the most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable, and fawning Royalist) will see more then now can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed; and yet here is the first fruits of our <hi>Kings</hi> and of their righteous Title, whose succession hath been as much in tyranny after him, as in title: and yet we must, by a sacred obligation be bound to maintain with our blood and lives, the branches of this rotten root, notwithstanding all the providential and divine opportunities
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109707:11"/> of casting off that miserable yoak which our forefathers, so sadly groaned under, and would have triumphed in the pouring out their blood (which they shed freely, but to little purpose) but to have foreseen their childrens children might have but the hopes of attaining to.</p>
            <p>But although <hi>William</hi> the First made sure his Conquest to his own Person, yet by his Tyranny he gave ground of designs, and hopes of recovery after his death, &amp; therefore the People who but murmured and mourned in secret formerly, consider now their condition, and that <hi>Robert</hi> the right Heir was wanting, and his second Son endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored to be set up, begin to capitulate, and repeat their former grievances: and to stand upon their terms, with the next Successors; But <hi>William Rufus</hi> who longed for the Crown, and saw what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage he had by his Brothers absence, through the mediation of <hi>Lanke-Frank</hi> the Arch-bishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (a Man for his Vertue and Learning in great Esteem with the People) got himself to be accepted, and Crowned King (with exclusion of his Elder Brother) by fair promises, and engagements to repeal his Fathers Laws, and of promoting the Liberties of the <hi>English</hi> (any probability being then taking to the poor people.) But no sooner had he got the Crown fastned on his Head, (and defeated his Brother in battle) but he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat all his own promises, follows directly his Fathers steps, grows excessive covetous, lays on intolerable Taxes, and merciless exactions, returns their longings, and hopes after their just Liberty into a sad Bondage and Slavery. The poor people having thus smarted for their credulity, and renewing their sense of their misery, under the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Tyrants, take heart once again, and refuse to admit any after his death, until (as Judge <hi>Thorpe</hi> well expresseth it in that forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Discourse) they were cheated into a second Election of <hi>Hen</hi> the first, his youngest Brother; for the People standing for their Liberties (and yet, alas, but negatively, rather to be freed from excess of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, than knowing what true freedom was) having felt the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery of their loss in the two former persons (shall I call them <hi>Kings?</hi>) Raign; denyed any consent to another person of that stock without solemn capitulations and covenants to settle just Laws, and to ingage for the execution of them, with abrogation of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer mischievous and inconvenient ones (which <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> calls unworthily a Politick, but traiterons way of capitulating.) Whereupon <hi>Henry,</hi> who had nothing of Title, made Friends by his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109707:11"/> engagements, and <hi>Roberts</hi> absence in the <hi>Holy-Land,</hi> and doth abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely promise to begin all anew, constitute just Laws, reform his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Brothers oxorbitances, and to be as a Nursing Father both to Church and State; these fair insinuations got him the Crown, though <hi>Robert</hi> was to have it first by his own right, and next by his Brother's Covenant and Will.</p>
            <p>And that he might not seem altogether disproportionable to his engagement, the first action of his government was to bait the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and sugar their Subjection, as his Predecessor in the like interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition had done, but with more moderation and advisedness (<hi>see Dan.</hi> Life of <hi>Henry</hi> I.) but having once secured his Title from his Brothers <hi>jus,</hi> and setled some affairs abroad, began much after the old strain (yet not altogether so violent) yet these cruel and savage Laws of the Forest, he revived, and put in execution, yea, urged as the most fundamental Law of the Realm, and many sore Impositions he le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied, which the People were not able to bear, that these two sons, tho they ended the direct Line, yet they propagated their Father's Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; only he got the Throne by Force, they by Subtilty, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusive engagements; and now the poor People, who had still been co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zened, and are commonly passive, begin in the next Kings reign, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Stephen</hi> another Usurper, to be active, and to struggle for their liberties more seriously and throughly, and not contented with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of abating former pressures, drew up the Sum of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires in a more exact method, and demand publickly the restoring and re-establishing of St. <hi>Edward's</hi> Laws, for such a rarity was that former Prince, as they canonized him a Saint, which were many years before granted, but by new and strange Successions buried, and <hi>Stephen,</hi> who came in odly to the Crown, and was continually in various Motions to maintain it, confirmed all these Laws, and to gain the People, ratifyed them by Parliament, the best security in these cases: But soon after Prerogative, like a Lion in chains, breaks forth again with fuller rage, and devours all these grants, with the hopes, and expectations of the people; for though in the two next Kings Reigns these grants were not actually repealed, yet were laid by, and only wrapt up in parchments, and husht by the noise of Drums, and Trumpets For <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, the next King, spent most of his time in clearing the Controversie, between <hi>Regnum &amp; Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> the Crown and the Mitre, as in setling his own Title both here, and in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> a while he and <hi>Thomas Becket</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:109707:12"/> were standing in the special Rights and Priviledges of the Church and State, the liberties of the people were laid asleep, and certainly he hated the former grants, because made by <hi>Stephen,</hi> I who had stolen the Crown both from his Mother, and himself; the notablest story in this Kings Reign (setting by his warlike atchievements) is, that after <hi>Becket</hi> had often foiled him in his Authority, he was hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somly whipt by the Monks, in going to visit <hi>Beckets</hi> shrine, which was part of his pennance, for giving secret order to Assassinats to make him away; And that he kept <hi>Rosamond</hi> as his Concubine, to the vexation of <hi>Elenor</hi> his Wife, who at last vented her revenge on her, having found her out in that intricate Labyrinth made on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose for her at <hi>Woodstock,</hi> by the clew which <hi>Rosamond</hi> had care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly untwisted.</p>
            <p>The next that laid claim to this Crown, was his Son <hi>Richard</hi> the First, Sir-named <hi>Ceur de Lion</hi> (as before) who was to be commended rather for his personal Valour, in other Nations, then for any good done to this; He began well in enlarging his Mother <hi>Elenor,</hi> whom his Father had im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>risoned, because she could not abide his lascivious living with his wanton Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agon <hi>Rosamond,</hi> and advanced many persons by special favours; yet these respects were more particular, then of any publick advantage to the State; for out of a blind zeal in those times, after he had been in <hi>England</hi> but four Months after his Coronation, he went into the <hi>Holy-land,</hi> against the <hi>Turks,</hi> leaving the Regency of the Kingdom to an Ecclesiastical Person <hi>William Lonchampe,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi> who to please the King, and by special Command, undid the People, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted great exactions, and as <hi>Hoveden</hi> says, <hi>Clerum &amp; populum oppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebat confundens fas{que} nefas{que}</hi> did all as he listed, and little cared by what means he filled the Kings Coffers, and his own; (acting but by Proxy and in imitation of what his Master would have done, if at home &amp; by many a private command) as it afterwards proved; for when <hi>Richard</hi> undertook his voyage, that he might not seem at first burthensom to the people when he left them, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain both his design, and absence on their purses (and so alienate the affections from him when at so great a distance, and give grounds to his Brother <hi>John</hi> to try an experiment for the Title) wisely sold much of his own Estate to raise him Monies, as the Castles of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Roxborough,</hi> to the King of <hi>Scots</hi> for ten thousand pounds, and the Lordship and Earldom of <hi>Durham,</hi> to <hi>Hugh</hi> then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109707:12"/> Bishop of that See, for much mony, as also many Honors, Lordships, Mannors, Offices, Priviledges, Royalties, to many of the Nobles, and rich Commoners, whereby he furnished himself with a vast trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury of mony for that service; and that you may see what interest he and his companions think they have in his peoples goods (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they dissemble it) he often protested that he would sell his City of <hi>London</hi> (as my Author saith) to any that would buy it rather then be chargeable unto others; but notwithstanding all this, as the people were sadly opprest in his absence by his Viceroy, so much more when he returned by himself; for he then began to redeem his time, and to play <hi>Rex</hi> with a witness; he fell presently to plunder all Religious Houses, laid on new and unheard of Taxes onthe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and resumed into his hands again all the Lordships, Mannors, Castles, &amp;c. which he had sold to his Subjects, and confirmed it by all the security they could have from man; this is the misery of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on Royal promises, and engagements, which are usually no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but complemental engins to move up the people affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, while they more easily, and insensibly drain out their Blood, and purses, this was the end of this Rough, and Lionlike King; who reigned nine years, and nine months, wherein he exacted and consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more of this Kingdom then all his Predecessors from the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had done before him, and yet less deserved it then any, having neither lived here, nor left behind him a monument of piety, or any publick work, or ever shewed love or care to this Common-wealth, but only to get what he could from it; we see hither to what a race of Kings we have had, and what cause we have to glory in any thing but their Tombs; and yet if we expect better afterwards, we shall be as much mistaken of their actings as they were of their right.</p>
            <p>The next that raigned (though without any hereditary Title) was King <hi>John, Stephens</hi> Brother; whose government was as unjust as his Title, for he (having by Election out of fear and policy of State, got the Crown, with expulsion of <hi>Arthur</hi> the right Heir <hi>ut supra</hi>) embarked the State, and himself in these miserable incumberances, through his violence and oppression, as produced desperate effects, and made way to those great alterations in the Government which followed; the whole reign of this King was a perfect Tyranny; there is in History hardly one good word given him; the Barons and Clergy continually opposed him, strugling for a confirmation of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109707:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:109707:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:109707:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:109707:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109707:15"/> their long desired Liberties, but were most commonly either cluded, or defeated by promises which were never intended to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, until at last being more entirely united with the Commons, and sloutly resolved and confirmed by an Oath, taken at St. <hi>Edmonds-Bury</hi> in a general Assembly, they then swore on the high Altar, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to lay down Arms, if King <hi>John</hi> refused to confirm and restore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them these Liberties (the rights which this Kingdom was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blest with, and which all the late Kings had cheated them of) the King knowing their power, and considering their engagements, makes use of policy, and desired time to answer them, entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with smooth and gentle Language, and courtesie, until he had got strength, and then he began anew to try experiments of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing himself, and frustrating their desires: But the Lords continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their resolution, and knowing nothing was to be obtained but by strong hand, assembled themselves with a great Army at <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> from whence they marched towards the King, who was then at <hi>Oxford;</hi> sent him a Schedule of their claimed Liberties, with an Appendix of their absolute resolutions, in case of his denyal; this Tyrant having heard them read, with much passion replies: <hi>Why do they not demand the Kingdom as well?</hi> and were he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver grant these Liberties, whereby himself should be made a servant: The Barons upon his Answer being (as <hi>Dainel</hi> saith) as hasty as he was averse, resolve to seaze on his Castles and Possessions; and repairing to <hi>London,</hi> being welcomed by the Citizens, who had too long groaned under the same Tyranny they get a great access of strength by new consederates, and renew their Spirits and Oaths for the thorow prosecution of the War; the King seeing himself in a strait, which by no ordinary strength he could evade, by gentle an teem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Messages sent to the Barons, he obtained a Conference in a Meadow called <hi>Running-mead,</hi> between <hi>Windsor</hi> and <hi>Stanes,</hi> where armed multitudes came from all places, crying nothing but <hi>Liberty, Liberty,</hi> so sweet was that tone to them then: After many hard Conferences, the King seeing it no time to dally, and that they would not trust him with any complemental expressions, whom they look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on as formerly perjured grants their desires; not only, saith <hi>Speed,</hi> for Liberties specified in <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and <hi>Charta Forrestae,</hi> but also for a kind of sway in the Government, by five and twenty selected Peers, who were to be as a check over the King, and his chief Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciar, and all his Officers to whom any appeal might be made in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109707:15"/> case of breach of any Article or priviledge confirmed by that Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; And now one would think the people were secure enough; but though they seem now to have the liberty, yet they had not the seisin; for presently the King having got new credit by the largness of his grants, gets liberty with less suspicion to undo all; and in a short time (pretending these grants to be acts of force) having got power, renounceth his engagement by them, and afterwards repeals them, and dispoiled all these of their Lands, and possessions, who had any hand or heart in procuring the former grants; and by new and additional Laws made them more perfect slaves then ever they were before, until at last he was poysoned by a Monk, instead of being deposed.</p>
            <p>But though he be dead, yet the miseries of this Nation ended not with him; for his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the Third; who succeeded him, though he could not at first follow on his Fathers designs, being an Infant, yet at last did not only imitate, but outstript him; yet the <hi>English</hi> Nation, (who are much given to credulity, and apt to be won by fair and plausible promises,) notwithstanding all the Fathers iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, imbrace the Son, having taken an Oath of him to restore, and confirm the Liberties they propounded to his Father, which he had often granted, and as often broken; but for all his first Oath, they were fain, not only to remember him of it, by petitions, but oftentimes by Arms and strength. And though there was in this Kings Raign twenty one Parliaments called, and many great Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidies granted, in confirmation of their Liberties, yet every Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was no sooner dissolved, but the ingagement ceased; a hint of two or three special Parliaments, and their success will not be amiss to be set down in this place.</p>
            <p>This <hi>King</hi> not being able to suppress the Barons and people by his own strength, (they having gotten not only heart, but power) sends to Forraign Nations for aid, and entertains <hi>Poictovines, Italians, Almains, Provincioes</hi> to subdue his own people, and set them in great places; which dangerous and desperate design the Barons much resenting, raised their Spirits, and ingaged them in opposition to his Government, and set them on with more courage to look after their Liberties; therefore they several times stand up against the violence of Prerogative; but what through want of strength or caution they were commonly disappointed; yet rather (if we may speak truly) from the unfaithfulness of the <hi>King</hi> then
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109707:16"/> any other defect, except it were their easiness to believe <hi>Kings,</hi> when their Prerogative, and the peoples Liberties came in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition; for after they had many times got, or rather extorted many promises, and confirmed them by Oaths, (the best human security) they were put to new designs, through either the suspension, or breach of them, witness these Instances, after many foiles, and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and various delusions by this <hi>King</hi> (whose beams attracted most, dazled others) the Barons, and people (who were then u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous through mutual oppressions) fall more close, and severe on their principles, and will not endure either delays, or delusions, and therefore effectually to redress their grievances, came very well Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to a Parliament then holden at <hi>Oxford</hi> (intended rather for getting Subsidies, then removing oppressions) in which Assembly they put the King to it, urge their former complaints with more zeal and reason, and with an addition of a mighty Spirit, demand the absolute confirmation of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and in a larger edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (wherein are comprised those Gallant Priviledges of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England,</hi> which have yet been but kept by Ink and Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and not trusting the King, got his Son, Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> to seal it, with an addition of twenty four (some writ twelve) Peers which <hi>Fabian</hi> stiles the <hi>douze Peeres,</hi> not only to see these Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges truly observed, but to be as joynt Regents with the King; and all the Lords, and Bishops in Parliament took a like Oath to maintain these Articles inviolable, yea, and all that wold have any benefit of residence in the Kingdom, were enjoyned to take the same; But these were too strict bonds for such a Princes will, he soon finding advantages (as he sought them) recals all, gets a dispensation from the Pope for his forced Oath and to countenance his perjury, and acts in the old account; the Barons again stand up with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple stoutly for the performance of the Articles of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brought him into straits; yea, fully defeated him in many Bloody Battels, and regained the confirmation of the same Laws, with security; that all the Castles through out <hi>England</hi> should be delivered to the keeping of the Barons, that the provisions of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> be inviolably preserved, that all strangers should be dismist the Kingdom, but those which by general consent should be thought sit to remain; this necessitous act though as it gave the people some peace and hopes, so it gave the King time to consider of new <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums,</hi> and therefore still to delay, and blind, he Assembles a new
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109707:16"/> Parliament at <hi>London,</hi> where having (by the sprinkling of Court water) won many Lords to take his part, begins to surprise as many of the Barons as he could get, and spoiled their Castles and Houses, that success and authority grows strong on his side, and the Barons with some calm provisoes mediate a peace, insisting only in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral that the Articles of <hi>Oxford</hi> might be observed; But the King relying on his strength, defies them as Traitors; which done, the Peoples two Generals, the Earls of <hi>Leicester</hi> and <hi>Glocester,</hi> seeing no other means but to put it to a day, supply their want of strength by their wit and diligence, and carefully and artificially placing their Battel (which was fought at the Town of <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Sussex</hi>) overthrew the Kings Army, took the King, the Prince, the Earl of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and his Son <hi>Henry,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Arundel, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> with many other Lords and Gentlemen, both <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Scottish.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having the King and Prince, and most of the Nobles, and a new confirmation of all, one would think the great Charter was out of danger, either of blotting or razing; especially if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the solemnities formerly used in the ratification of it, (as <hi>Daniel</hi> excellently relates it in his History <hi>p.</hi> 169.) The People knowing that no civil Promises, or verbal Professions would hold in Kings rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured by Prerogative and devoted to Perjury to maintain their Tyranny, take a more Ecclesiastical and divine way of obligation, swearing to excommunicate all that should be found Infringers of that Charter; when the People with the King, and all the great No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility were assembled with all the Prelates, and the chief Bishops in their reverent Ornaments (with burning Candles in their hands) to receive that dreadful sentence; the King having one great Candle in his hand, gives it to a Prelate that stood by, saying, it becomes not me being no Priest to hold this Candle, my heart shall be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter testimony; and withall laid his hand spread on his Breast all the while the sentence was pronouncing, which was <hi>Autoritate om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotentis Dei,</hi> &amp;c. which done, he caused the Charter of King <hi>John</hi> his Father to be read, and in the end having thrown away their Candles (which lay smoaking on the ground) they cryed out, <hi>so let them that incur this sentence be extinct and stink in Hell:</hi> And the King with a loud voice said, <hi>As God help I will, as I am a man; a Christian, a Knight, a King Crowned and Annointed, inviolably observe these things.</hi> Never were Laws saith he (whose words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109707:17"/> the thing most emphastically amongst men (except those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Commandments from the Mount) established with more Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty of Ceremony, to make them reverenced and respected, than these were; they wanted but Thunder and Lightning from Heaven, (which likewise if Prayers could have effected they would have had it) to make the sentence ghastly, and hideous to the breakers of it; the greatest security that could be given was an Oath (the only chain on Earth besides love) to tye the Conscience of a Man, and human society together; which should it not hold us, all the frame of Government must needs fall quite asunder; yet so (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most a Miracle (though over common among our Kings, saith Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> out of <hi>Mat. Paris p.</hi> 8. 9.) the Parliament being thus dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved (by a sacred and most solemn conclusion) the King present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly studies how to infringe all the premises, his Parasites telling him the Pope could soon absolve him for a sum of Money, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Pope did, and the King returned to his former oppressive courses with more violence, and hardness; and taking advantage by the division of the Barons, two Generals, the Earls of <hi>Leicester</hi> and <hi>Glocester,</hi> the latter of which joyned with the young Prince <hi>Edward</hi> and Sir <hi>Roger Mortimer</hi> the Kings wicked Counsellor, a new and potent Army is raised by them, against the Earl of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> (who had the King Prisoner) and those which kept constant with him, for the Peoples Liberties; and he with the rest of the Barons are overthrown; and immediately after a Parliament is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and all these Laws and Decrees made void; and that Parliament held at <hi>Oxford,</hi> wherein all these Laws were first confirmed by him, called <hi>Insanum Parliamentum,</hi> the mad Parliament; and all these Patents, Commissions or Instruments made to ratifie these Articles, were brought forth, and solemnly damned; and so bright and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>splendent did Prerogative break forth, that it was Proclaimed Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in any but to speak or mention any of these Grants with the least approbation; and because the City of <hi>London</hi> had engaged with the Barons and People as a principle Part of the whole, he would needs have burnt the City, had not some wise and potent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites interposed, and yet they could hardly disswade him from that barbarous and impolitick wickedness; but what he spared in their Houses, that he got out of their Purses, and made up all his losses with a thorough subjection of their Persons, and suppression of their Liberties. I need relate no more of this King, nor make ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109707:17"/> the Reader will be amazed at the repetition; he at least twenty times gave his promise for the conformation, and execution of these just decrees (contained in <hi>Megna Charta</hi>) and as many times was perjured, notwithstanding all the solemnities, both Civil, Moral, and Ecclesiastical, used in the acts of ratification; this may learn us how to trust the most possitive Engagements of Princes, which cross their own interest, and what to think of that word and promise they call Royal; this King reigned fifty six years, the longest of any King of <hi>England:</hi> But we have had too much of the story of him, as he had too long a time to Rule, considering his ten per and design. Its well if we can be wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y for the future, and be more cautious then to trust the most promising and insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating Princes with our Liberties and Priviledges, which can be no longer expected to be preserved by them, then they may serve as scotst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ols to advance them in the Throne of absolute Majesty: But no more of this King; never were there more hard strivings and wrestlings between Tyranny and Liberty with such had success to the People; I only conclude his Reign with the Exhortation of the Psalmist, <hi>Psal. 146. O put not your confidence in Princes,</hi> sUrely Men of high degree are a lye.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> is by this time laid in his Grave, and one would think <hi>Magna Charta</hi> buried with him; his Son <hi>Edward,</hi> who was his right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand in his Wars against the Barons, and the principal Agent in their ruine, succeeds him in the Throne; and instead of lessoning goes on and makes an higher improvement of that Royalty which his Father left him; having in his own person got the victory over the Peoples Liberties in his Fathers time, and having won or worn out the greatest of those which opposed, and being long experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the World, so secured and advanced the Prerogative, that as one saith, be seemed to be the first Conqueror after the Conqueror that got the domination of this State in so absolute and eminent a manner, as by his Government appears; He laid unsupportable Taxes both on the Clergy and Laity, even unto Fifteens and halfs of their Estates. As for Tenths, that was comparatively accounted easy; the Barons and People for a long time durst not move for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of greivances, until that the King (being always in Wars in <hi>France, Flanders, Wales</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and so needed continually vast sums of Money) called a Parliament wherein he demanded a great treasure of Money from the People, that he might give them
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109707:18"/> somewhat in lieu of their expences, confirmed the two great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on the Petition of the Barons and People, (and so stopped their Mouths) and this he did as often as he had extraordinary occasions for Money; But (like all other Royal promises) they were perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by leasure. Never was Royalty more Majestick and Glorious then in this Kings Raign, and the People less able to oppose; he was always so watchful and eager to enlarge his own power; I shall end his Raign, also with what <hi>Daniel</hi> that impartial and witty Historian faith of him, He was more for the greatness of the Kingdom then the quiet of it; and never <hi>King</hi> before or since (<hi>except the late Civil Wars</hi>) shed so much Christian blood within this Isle of <hi>Britain,</hi> and was the cause of more in that following, and not one grain of benefit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured unto the People by all their expences on him, which was but to make themselves more perfect slaves.</p>
            <p>The next King was <hi>Edward</hi> the Second his Son, who though more vicious than the Father, yet not more Tyrannical; he gave more advantage to the People through his leud life and unmartial na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to seek the confirmation and establishment of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other good Laws which were utterly supprest, and darkened in his Fathers raign. This Prince gave himself over to all wicked courses, and surrendred his Judgement, and the management of all affairs of State unto evil and corrupt Counsellors; especially to one <hi>Peirce Gaveston,</hi> who had both his Ear and Heart, unto whom he was so much endeared, that he ventured the loss of <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and all the Hearts of his Subjects for his company and preservation; and though the Barons had by often Petitions, and earnest solicitations prevailed with the King to banish him, yet he soon after sent for him home, and laid him more nigh his bosom then before; on this the Barons raise an Army against the King; and send him word, that unless he would observe the late Articles (which they had formerly by much ado got him to sign in Parliament) and put from him <hi>Peirce Gaveston,</hi> they would rise in Arms against him as a perjured Prince; the <hi>King</hi> (whom they found, was apt to be terrified) yields again to his banishment, with this clause, that if he were found again within the <hi>Kingdom</hi> he should be condemned to death as an Enemy of the State. All places were now dangerous to <hi>Gaveston;</hi> both <hi>Ireland</hi> (where he formerly was protected), and <hi>France</hi> also too hot for him; in this extremity, finding no security any where else, he again adventures on <hi>England,</hi> and puts himself once again into the Kings
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109707:18"/> bosom (a Sanctuary which he thought would not be polluted with blood) and there he is received with as great joy as ever Man could be; the Lords with more violence prosecute their suit to the <hi>King</hi> for delivering up, or removing him once more, but to no purpose; they therefore set forwards with an Army, lay siege to the Castle wherein <hi>Gaveston</hi> was, took him, and notwithstanding the <hi>Kings</hi> earnest solicitation for his life, they condemned him to the Block, and took off his Head; this obstacle being removed out of the way, the Lords having now the better end of the staff make advantages of it for demanding the confirmation, and execution of all those Articles formerly granted, threatning the <hi>King,</hi> that if he would not consent to it, they would force him by a strong hand; with this message they had their Swords also drawn, and march towards <hi>London:</hi> A Parliament is called, where the <hi>King,</hi> after a submission by the Lords to him for that act done against <hi>Gaveston,</hi> contrary to his consent, and will, grants the Articles and pardon to them. But the <hi>King</hi> goes on his old way, adheres to wicked counsel (waving the grave advice of his Parliament) and is ruled by the two <hi>Spencers,</hi> who acted with mighty strain of injustice, which causEd the Lords again to take up Arms, and stand for their Liberties, but are, through the revolt of some, and the treachery of others overthrown at <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> upon <hi>Trent,</hi> and two and twenty Noblemen, the greatest Peers in the Realm executed in several places for nothing but opposing his evil Counsellors: this was the first blood of Nobility that ever was shed in this manner in <hi>England</hi> since <hi>William</hi> the First, which being so much, opened Veins for more to follow; and now the beam of power being turned, regality weighs down all. But by degrees, through the continuation of his ill government, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he daily lost the Peoples hearts, the Lords get an Army, and take the King Prisoner, and by general consent in Parliament de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed him as a Tyrant, and elected his Son <hi>Edward</hi> the Third to succeed, and his Son was crowned before his Eyes. Thus ended his Reign, but not his life.</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>England</hi> which had laboured so long and successively under so many Tyrants, and had contested so long with Royalty for their dearly purchased Liberties, might now hopefully expect, at least a dawning of Reformation, especially when they had got so much power as to depose Authority; and began, as it were, on a new account; and the truth is, affairs were now promising, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109707:19"/> distempers seemed to wear away with the former Governor; yet the condition of the Kingdom, had but a new face on it, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances were rather not aggravated or multiplied than any whit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and oppressions may be rather laid to be charged from one Shoulder to another then abolished.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Edward</hi> who succeeded, who was crowned in his fathers life, had observance enough to remember his fate, and was much warned by it, both to prevent and suppress insurrections, knowing by experience the full state of the Controversie, and therefore began his Government very fairly, and with much applause; only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent factions, and sidings, he privately caused his father, the deposed <hi>King</hi> to be cruelly murthered, and so sate more securely, though with more guilt upon the Throne; his Reign was fifty years, and odd Months, the longest next <hi>Henry</hi> the Third; he spent most of his time in the Wars of <hi>France</hi> to regain his Title to that Crown; which the poor Subject felt in their Estates and Families, and it was a happiness (say some) that he was so much abroad; for when ever he came home, as he wanted Money to supply his Expences, so the People got ground to urge their Priviledges, and <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was at least twelve times ratified in this Kings Raign, and so often broken; yet because he goes under the name of the best Prince that raigned so long, and so well, let the Reader take but an Instance or two concerning his engagements to perform the grand Charter. This King in the first Parliament made the fifteenth year of his Reign, had granted the enacting of divers wholsom and seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Laws, which he willed and ingaged unto for him and his Heirs, that they should <hi>be firmly kept, and remain inviolable for ever,</hi> for the ratification of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other good Laws formerly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted; and that all the Officers of State, as Chancellor, Treasurer, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Exchequer, Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> should at that present in Parliament, and for ever after, take a solemn Oath before their admission to their Offices, to keep and maintain the point of the great Charter, and the Charter of the Forrest, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But no sooner was the Parliament dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved, but the very same year he publickly revoked these Statutes, pretending <hi>that they were contrary to the Laws and Customs of the Realm, and to his Prerogative and Rights Royal, &amp;c.</hi> wherefore we are willing (saith he) providently to revoke these things we have so improvidently done; <hi>because</hi> (saith he) mark the dissimulation of Princes (even in Parliaments) <hi>We never really consented to the making
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109707:19"/> of such Statutes,</hi> but as then it behoved <hi>Ʋs, We dissembled in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises,</hi> by Protestations of revocation, if indeed they should proceed to secure the dangers, which by denying the same we feared to come, with many more such passages; and yet this King is the Phoenix of our more antient Monarchs; but the Reader may still learn what the best of our Princes have been, and what weak assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances any ingagements from them are, where power is wanting from them and advantages present to them.</p>
            <p>Another instance of his actings we may take up from the success of his first siege of <hi>Tourney</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> having laid on heavy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive taxes to maintain that war, and the people seeing no fruits of all promises for executing the Articles of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to pay any more, without more faithful performance of his Vows, and solemn engagements to them, whereby he wanting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was fain to quit the place, and return for <hi>England,</hi> full of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful thoughts, and in much fury breaths out destruction to all the refusers; But the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> told him publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but plainly, that he had oftentimes as well as his Father offered manifest violences to the Liberties of the <hi>English</hi> Nation, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in that grand Charter, and if he expected Subsidies, from the people, he must more carefully maintain their priviledges so justly due. But the <hi>King</hi> vexed with such language, both storms against the Arch-bishop, and as much as possibly he then could sought the ruine of all that had made any refusal of payment of these taxes, although he had not in any manner performed his own promises. Yet I will end his Reign, because he hath the name of a good <hi>King,</hi> (though as <hi>Speed</hi> saith, by the General vote of Historians, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted many foul Errors in his Government) with a good act he did at the fiftieth year of his age (which he kept as his Jubilee) he called a Parliament, and there freely heard the grievances of the people, and redressed many, especially a Petition of the Commons against the doublings of Lawyers; he caused the pleas which were before in <hi>French</hi> to be made in <hi>English; a necessary Law</hi> (saith <hi>Speed</hi>) if it had been as carefully observed, especially if he had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered (saith he) that the same should not have been written in <hi>French, That the Subject might understand the Law by which he holds what he hath, and is to know what he doth.</hi> But all this is not for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; for as he imparted grace unto his people (faith the same Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) for so all acts of Justice are termed, when granted by Kings,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109707:20"/> so he took a care to replenish his own Purse by it, that the poor Commons obtain not any thing which they pay not too dearly for.</p>
            <p>Here ends the Life of the best reputed Prince; and yet you see wherein his excellency lay; the best happiness the People had in his Raign, was, that they had more Engagements for their Liberties with more cost, and the remembrances and sense of the goodness of them more fresh and sweet by the often repetition of them; but for execution or addition to them, they were as far to seek as in former times. And if it do possibly happen that in one Kings Raign either through the goodness of his Nature, or rather want of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, there be an intermission of oppressions; (for that is the utmost to be expected) yet the next King will be sure to make it up, and if they give the People a little breadth, its but that they may sow for the next to reap, or as they do with Men on the Rack, let them down, and give them Cordials, and spiritful Liquors, that they may be the longer and more sensibly tormented; which was made good in the next Kings raign, <hi>viz. Richard</hi> the Second, who presently dashes and utterly nips these blossoms that sprung out in the former Kings raign, devoting himself to all uncivil and lewd courses, and to enable him the better unto it, lays on sad and miserable Taxes on the People without so much as a mention or hint of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and as the parrallel of <hi>Ed.</hi> the Second, both lived and died; Its enough to decypher his raign by his end; for he was deposed by the universal consent of the People in Parliament as a tyrannical and cruel Governor, and not a good word spoken of him to commend him in his Government, and its pitty to aggravate his misery after his death, and yet (as we say) <hi>Seldom comes a better;</hi> when one is cut off, another like the Hidra's head springs up in his place. <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth who overthrew him in Battle, and was made <hi>King</hi> in his stead (though by a wrong Title) at first promised the new model<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Laws to the Peoples ease, and did, as in a complement (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to secure his Titile, then out of affection to the People, or sense of his relation) redress many grievances, which were more gross and less concerning the Common-wealth; and as he did strive by these common acts to engage the People to him, so (as one that had continual sence of guilt on him) he got the deposed King to be barbarously murthered in the Castle of <hi>Pomfret,</hi> that no competiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might endanger his Title by his life, He spent most of his raign
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109707:20"/> in continual Wars about his Title, and was often opposed as both a Tyrant and Usurper; but he still got ground on both the Liberties and Laws formerly granted; yet not so sensibly as in the former Kings Reigns, that the People may be said to have a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spite from the Violence and Height of Prerogative by him; but they may thank the Unjustness and Bitterness of his Title, for that he being more in fear of loosing it, than out of Love with the Excess of his Ancestors. I shall only add one Story to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Kings Reign, which is universally reported by most of our Historians, worth observation, because it hath much of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity in it, and because they were his dying Words; being cast into an Apoplexy, and nigh his End, he caused his Crown to be placed by him on his Pillow, least in the Extremity of his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness it might have been delivered to some other, who had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Right thereunto than he had; but when his Attendants, (through the Violence of his Distemper) supposed him to be dead, the young Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> seised on his Crown, whereat the King started up, raising himself on his Arms, demanded who it was that had so boldly taken away the Crown? the Prince an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered that it was he, the King fell back into his Bed, and fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a deep Sigh, and sending forth many a pensive Groan, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies thus; My Son, what Right I had to this Crown, and how I have enjoyed it, God knows, and the World hath seen: But the Prince (ambitious enough of a Diadem) answered him thus; Comfort your self in God (good Father) the Crown you have, and if you dye, I will have it, and keep it with my Sword, as you have done, and so he did soon after, maintaining his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Injustice by his own.</p>
            <p>And now comes up his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth as the next Heir, who though while a Prince was given to many wicked Practises, yet when a King became moderate, and hath better Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than most of his Ancestors; the People had two Advantages and Comforts by him; first, that his Reign was short, and that he was much imployed in the War with <hi>France,</hi> for regaining a Title to that Crown, which he accomplished, and so they were free of Civil Wars; though they had still heavy Taxes, yet they thought it better to pay for maintaining War abroad than at Home, and truly, the People thought themselves very happy in this Kings Reign, (though their Privileges were laid asleep) that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109707:21"/> they had little breathing time from Domestick and Civil Wars, and had hopes to regain by degrees a reviving of their Spirits.</p>
            <p>But the next King, <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, makes up what was wanting of Tyranny and Oppression in his Fathers Reign. He was crowned King about the eighth or ninth Month of his Age, and so had not present opportunity to shew his Royalty. Until he came to Age, the Kingdom was well governed by his three Uncles, <hi>Humphrey</hi> Duke of <hi>Glocester, John</hi> Duke of <hi>Bedford, Thomas</hi> Duke of <hi>Exeter;</hi> who by their Wisdom and Justice, kept up the flourishing Estate of the <hi>English</hi> Nation; but when his Years of Nonage were expired, and he came to weld the Scepter with his own Hands, (what as some favourably think out of Weakness, for he was no <hi>Solomon</hi>) all things went presently out of order, and Prerogative breaks forth beyond bounds; which gave occasion to <hi>Edward</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> to try Conclusions for his Title against the House of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and making use of the Discontents of the People through his evil Government, opposed him, and afterwards deposed him, and reigned in his stead by the Name of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, and so by Conquest he got the Title to run through the House of <hi>York,</hi> having cut it off by his Sword from the House of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> notwithstanding actual Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of three Descents, many Overtures of War were yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them; for <hi>Henry</hi> was not yet dead, though for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent outed, but as a dying Man strove for Life, but being quite overthrown, was imprisoned, and afterwards murthered to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Title; there was in these two Kings Reign, but meerly for a Title, fought ten bloody Battles, besides all lesser Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishes, wherein many thousands of Lords, Gentlemen and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were slain, and yet not one jot of Advantage gotten by it for the Peoples Liberties; it being the Misery and Folly of the People, to venture all they have, to set up those over them, who afterwards prove most Tyrannical, and to low Seeds of future Misery, by spilling their Bloods for an usurped Title.</p>
            <p>In this Kings Reign, as in the former, the whole Land was miserably rent by unnatural Divisions against his Title and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and though neither or these two had a just Title (if, we will begin from the Root) yet all the Blood of the Nation is thought too little to be spilt to maintain their Pretences; yet we may not reckon this King among the worst, had it not fallen out
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109707:21"/> that his Title must be kept up with Expence of so much Blood, and Ruine of the <hi>English</hi> Nation; yet in his last five years, he laid on such extraordinary Taxes, and changed the Form of Laws, that he lost the Love of all his Subjects.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Edward</hi> the Fifth his Son, who succeeded him in Title, we need but mention him, for he had but the Name of a King (being an Infant) and his Reign may well be called an <hi>Inter reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> for e're he came to know what Government was, he was cruelly murthered with his Infant Brother, by his Uncle <hi>Rich.</hi> Duke of <hi>Glocester,</hi> who reigned both for him, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards for himself, by the Name of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, a bloody and cruel Man, rather a Monster than a Prince, his Name stincks in the English Dialect; the shortness of his Reign was the Happiness of the People; for after three years Usurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he was slain in the Field by the Earl of <hi>Richmond,</hi> who by his Valour, more than is Title, got the Crown, by the Name of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh; this was the best Act that was done by him, in easing the Kingdom of such a Viper. In his Reign (who is the first Root of our Kings since) the People had more Hopes than Benefits, and were rejoyced and made happy more by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, than Enjoyments of any real Priviledge or Liberty. For though he took all the ways to secure his Title, by his Marriage to the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, yet many Stratagems were laid to disturb his Peace, which put him on Acts of Policy and Diligence (which he excellently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated) to free and extricate himself out of Dangers and Designs; many sad Divisions were still in the Kingdom, all men were not pleased either with his Title or Government, and that they might but disturb him, or hazard his Crown, they made Stage-Kings, drest up pretty Lads in princely Robes, and carried them up and down the Kingdom as Puppets for the People to gaze on and admire; all this while King <hi>Henry</hi> had not time to advance his Prerogative, while he was but securing his Title; but after he had done that, and now began to look on himself as free from either foreign or home Competitors, and the Coast of State seeming clear from all thickning Weather, he thinks of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming what he had lost by Factions, and imploys his Wit for bringing down the heighth of the <hi>English</hi> Nation, and plucking down their Courage, and was especially (saith one) jealous over
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109707:22"/> his Nobility, as remembring how himself was set up; and how much more did this Humor encrease in him after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with such Idols and Counterfeits as <hi>Lambert, Simnel</hi> and <hi>Perkin Warbeck?</hi> the strangeness of which Dangers made him think nothing safe; and thinking that the Riches of the <hi>English</hi> occasioned their Rebellions, he took a Course to empty their Coffers into his; and the Plot whereby he meant to effect it, was by taking the Advantage of the Breach of Penal Laws, which he both found, and made for that purpose; his Instruments which for this Work were pickt, and qualified sufficiently, were Sir <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Empson,</hi> and <hi>Edmund Dudley,</hi> Men learned in the Law, and of desperate and subtle Heads, and forward in executing the Kings Commands, these two attended by Troops of base Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Promoters, Catch-poles, Cheaters, Knights of the Post, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> went up and down the Kingdom, cruelly polled and taxed all sorts of People, and prosecuted in every Shire the most deserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and generous Men, that the Kingdom in a little time was more beggar'd, than by most of the Civil Wars; and all this done by the Kings special Command and Countenance, that we may see what was the reason he began not sooner to play the <hi>Rex;</hi> want of Opportunity, and fear of loosing his Crown while he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing it; but the latter end of his Reign was too soon, and too long for such Actings. This King ends his Reign with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Acts of Tyranny; he made himself a rich King by beggering his Subjects, after he had freed his own Person out of danger, he imploys all his Wits to enslave the <hi>English;</hi> the Fruits both of his Title and Tyranny, we have felt ever since, in these that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him.</p>
            <p>His Son <hi>Henry,</hi> the Eight of that Name, succeeds him; in his first beginnings he seemed to be tenderly affected to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and redressed many Grievances, especially those which were laid on by his Father, and executed by <hi>Empson</hi> and <hi>Dudley,</hi> doing Justice on them for their Cruelty and Oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But those Affections were too good, and too violent to last long; the Sound of Drums and Trumpets soon quasht them, and many Encroachments grew on the Peoples Liberties; many tempestuous Storms and Controversies there were in this Kings Reign; but they were more Ecclesiastical than Civil, and so more dangerous and strong. In a Word, he was accounted a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109707:22"/> better Souldier than a Governour, and more fit for a General than a King to govern by just and unequal Laws; the best Act he did, was the Discovery of the Wickedness of the Clergy, and casting off the Popes Supremacy, which yet he took to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and annexed it to his own Crown; as the most of his Reign was full of Controversies and Tempests, so all Affairs were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged in a ranting and turbulent manner, not with that Gravity and Soberness as becomes civil and prudential Transactions; he was very Lascivious, and delighted much in Variety and Changes of Laws, as Wives; he oftentimes much pleased himself to be in the Company, and was over-familiar with swaggering and loose Fellows; and the People ever and anon found the Power of his Prerogative at home, as his Enemies did of his Sword abroad. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, his only Son succeeds him, a Prince that was too good to live long, the Phoenix of <hi>English</hi> Kings, had he had time to prosecute his Intentions, and mature his Genius; but the Sun in him did shine too bright in the Morning; God gave <hi>England</hi> only the Representation of a good King, but would not in Judgment let us be blest long with him; Religion began to revive, Liberty to bud forth, the People to peep out of their Graves of Slavery and Bondage, and to have their Blood fresh and blusHing in their Cheeks; but all is presently blasted by his Death, and the People (who have seldom more than Hopes for their Comforts) are now fainting for fear; <hi>England</hi> is benighted, and hung with black. Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> that <hi>Alecto,</hi> and fury of Women, succeeds, and now both Souls and Bodies of the Poople are enslaved, and nothing but Bone-fires made of the Flesh and Bones of the best Christians: But its too much to name her in the <hi>English</hi> Tongue; Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> succeeds her, who being prepared for the Crown by suffering, came in a most seasonable time, both for her self and the People, who were made Fuel for the Flames of her Sisters Devotion.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>England</hi> begins to flourish again, and to recover its Strength; many Inlargments were granted, both to the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and Estates of the People; yet if we speak impartially, we were kept further off <hi>Rome</hi> than Royalty; yet doubtless she may be Chronicled for the best Princess, and her Reign the most even, and best managed, with more Fruits to the People than any of the former Kings, especially if we consider how long she govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109707:23"/> this Nation; I end her Reign with this Character, That she was the best Queen that ever <hi>England</hi> had, and the Glory of her Sex to all Ages.</p>
            <p>The <hi>English</hi> Line is now ended, we must go into <hi>Scotland</hi> to seek for a King, because a Daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh was married to <hi>James</hi> the Fourth, King of <hi>Scotland;</hi> but I will not question his Title.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> the Sixth of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and first of <hi>England,</hi> suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded on the <hi>English</hi> Throne; a Prince that had many Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to set up Prerogative, which he improved; he was too ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous to act, but most subtle in Councel and Designs, and no King did more insensibly and closely undermine the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> than himself; he gave us cause to remember from whence he came; but his peaceable Reign was the Rail to his Design, and did chaok Suspition; we were brought by him very nigh <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and yet knew it not; he had an invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Hatred against Puritans, as he had a Fear of Papists, and made more of Bishops than ordinary, by remembrance of the <hi>Scots</hi> Presbytery; he had as much of Royalty in his Eye as any Prince could have, but had not so much Courage to prosecute it; the Puritan always lay in his Spleen, the Papist on his Lungs, that he durst not, that he could not breath so clearly and strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against them; but the Bishops lay in his Heart. I will not rip up his personal Failings after his Death; he was the most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane King for Oaths and Blasphemies that <hi>England</hi> had besides, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He now grows old, and was judged only fit to lay the Plot, but not no execute it; the Design being now ripe, and his Person and Life the only Obstacle and <hi>Remora</hi> to the next Instrument, he is conveyed away suddenly into another World, as his Son <hi>Henry</hi> was, because thought unsutable to the Plot, it being too long to wait, until Nature and Distemper had done the Deed.</p>
            <p>We are now come to <hi>Charles</hi> the First, the perfect <hi>Idea</hi> of all the rest, and the most zealous Prosecutor of the Designs of all his Ancestors, who, if Divine Providence had not miraculously pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, had accomplished the utmost of their Intentions, and for ever darkned the Glory of the <hi>English</hi> Sun; so much I must say of him, that he got more Wisdom by Action, than could possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be expected by his Nature; Experience that teacheth Fools, made him wise; he endeavoured to act what others designed;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109707:23"/> he dissembled as long as he could, and used all Parties to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most; but his Zeal and Hardiness brought him to his Death. He needed no Physick for his Body, had he remembred his Soul. But what need I mention him? he would have been what other Kings are, and endeavoured to attain what others would be; he lived an Enemy to the Common-wealth, and dyed a Martyr to Prerogative.</p>
            <p>Thus you have seen a faithful Representation of the <hi>Norman</hi> Race, under which we have groaned for about six hundred years; the first Title made only by the Invasion and Conquest of a Stranger and Bastard, continued by Usurpation and Tyranny, that take away but two or three Persons out of the List (and yet these bad enough if we consider all things) and all this while <hi>England</hi> neither had a right Heir, or good King to govern it; and yet by Delusion and Deceit, we must be bound to maintain that Title as Sacred and Divine, which in the beginning was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted, and usurping, as if gray Hairs could add Reverence to Injustice. For my part, as I do not give much to that Monkish Prophecy from <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's Times; <hi>Mars, Puer, Alecto, Virgo, Vulpes, Leo, Nullus</hi> (yet I wonder how the Devil could foresee so far off, and must needs say, that it hath yet been lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally fulfilled, both in the Characters of the Persons of most of our Kings.</p>
            <p>Can we think (and retain our Memories and Reasons) that <hi>Charles</hi> the Second can forget <hi>Charles</hi> the First; that Custom and Education can easily be altered? that the true and real Engagers with him and his Father, shall be raised out of his Heart, or that he can heartily love his Opposers, but as he may make use of them? or that when some Banks and Rocks are out of the way, the Waters and Floods of Tyranny will not run in its wonted Channel? Can reason think or dream, that Breach of Coronation Oaths will not eat out Sincerity? or that Law and Liberty can flourish in that State where boundless Prerogative is the Ascendaut? or is that Person fit to be the <hi>Medium</hi> of Peace, and the Glory of this Nation, who was the conjunct Instrument of the War, and the Survivor both of the War and Peace? a Person that durst not stay in his own Nation to plead his Right because of his Guilt, whose Youth and Wilfulness is most un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>apt for the setling the Storms and Tempests of a distracted Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109707:24"/> It was said of <hi>Tiberius Caesar</hi> in a Satyrical Expression, yet it proved true.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ton. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 3. c. 52.</note> Regnabit Sanguine multo,</l>
               <l>Ad Regnum quisquis venit Sanguine multo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who first exil'd, is after Crown'd,</l>
               <l>His Reign with Blood will much abound.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Certain it is, that never any Prince, so long exterminated as he had been, was restored with more Alacrity and Unanimity of the People, with greater Applause and Expectaions, and with louder Acclamations of Joy and Triumph. For all which, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did any Prince so well require the Kindness of his doting Subjects, as our second <hi>Charles,</hi> grateful to the highest Degree, in yielding, and poorly submitting to the Counsels of all those that sought to betray their Properties and Liberties to <hi>French</hi> Slavery and Arbitrary Power, and give up their Religion first to the Subjection, and then to the Revenge of <hi>Rom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For when our Second <hi>Charles</hi> returned into <hi>England,</hi> true it was, that the Ballance of <hi>Europe</hi> was on the <hi>French</hi> side, and that by the Assistance of <hi>Cromwel,</hi> who for his own Ends, had sacrificed the Interest of the Nation, by joyning with the stronger Side, to suppress the Power of <hi>Spain,</hi> which it became him to have sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported. But when <hi>Charles</hi> the Second returned, all the World knows that he was followed with the Courtships of all the Nations abroad, to be speak the Friendship of a Prince, who, besides his other Greatness, was much more considerable, by his being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>established with the Love of his People. <hi>France</hi> saw this, and therefore to put the King of <hi>England</hi> into such a Condition that he might not be able to give any Opposition to his Designs upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> for which he had an incurable Passion, resolved to commit a Rape upon the Lady, which he could not otherwise win to his Embraces: A thing that he knew would not be easie to accomplish, so long as <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> were agreed, and resolved to rescue her, whenever they resolved to cry out to them for Help. To which end, the <hi>French</hi> King gave those <hi>Philters</hi> to the King of <hi>England,</hi> which contrary to the Nature of Love potions, that when they have done working, cause an Aversion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109707:24"/> for them that gave them, made our <hi>Charles</hi> the Second so in love ever afterward with the Person that gives them, as made him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver afterwards dote upon the King of <hi>Franee's</hi> Charms and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels till he had almost ruin'd the Nation, only leaving a little for his Brother to consummate; for whom he had such an Affection, so entire and baneful to this Nation, that he might be only said to Reign while his Brother Rul'd.</p>
            <p>Well then, to dissolve this Union between the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> we must be set together by the Ears. To this purpose <hi>Amboyna</hi> and the Fishery were talked of here, and the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Trade, and the Freedom of the Sea were disputed in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and there being combustible Matter enough on both sides, it took fire in a little time. What vast Supplies were furnished out by the Subject for defraying that War, is too well known, and yet after all, saving one brisk Engagement, ill managed, though with some Loss to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> at length no Fleet set out, and the choicest of the Royal Navy, either burnt or taken in their Harbours to save Charges. While the <hi>French,</hi> during that War, joyned themselves in Assistance with the <hi>Dutch</hi> against Us, and yet by the Credit he had with the Queen-Mother, so far delud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, that upon Assurance that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> would have no Fleet out at Sea that Year, no more than himself, forbore to make ready, and so incurred that shamful Disgrace at <hi>Chatham,</hi> the like to which the <hi>English</hi> never suffered since they claimed the Dominion of the Sea. And which was more, as he had been beholding to the King of <hi>France,</hi> for the Ignominy he had suffered, so was he glad to receive the Peace from his Favour, which was concluded at <hi>Breda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now the King of <hi>England</hi> was at leisure to observe how the <hi>French</hi> King had taken his Opportunity, while we were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyled and weakned by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> though with the Violation of the most Sacred Oaths and Treaties, and had invaded and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked a great Part of the <hi>Spanish Netherlands,</hi> which had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways considered as the Natural Frontier of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alarmed the King of <hi>England</hi> to that Degree, that he entered into a Defensive League with <hi>Holland,</hi> and made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for opposing the farther Progress of the <hi>French</hi> in the <hi>Spanish Netherlands.</hi> The <hi>Swede</hi> also shortly after made a Third in the Confederacy; from whence it was called the Triple Alliance.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:109707:25"/>
            <p>But in a very short time, these Counsels, which had taken ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect so much to the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Honour, and the general Satisfaction of the Nation, were all changed of a sudden. For the King of <hi>France</hi> being stopt in his Career by the Triple League, and by the Peace of <hi>Aix la Chapelle,</hi> soon after concluded, though for a while he dissembled his Dis-satisfaction, yet he resolved to untie the Triple Knot, whatever it cost him. To which purpose, the Dutchess of <hi>Orleans</hi> was sent over, as one who would be a welcome Guest to her Brother, and whose Charms and Dexterity joyned with her other Advantages, would give her such an Ascendant over him, as could not fail of Success. And indeed she quitted her self so well of the Commission, a double lay'd Foundation for a new strict Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> quite contrary to that wherein the King of <hi>England</hi> had been so lately engaged; which made him soon lookt upon by the Confederates as an Apostate from the common Interest. And this invisible <hi>French</hi> League was struck up with <hi>France</hi> to that height of Dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Affection, as if upon the ensuing sudden Death of the Princess, the Reconciliation with <hi>France</hi> had not been to have been celebrated with a less Sacrifice than that of the Blood Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this <hi>French</hi> League being made in the Dark, and as yet undiscovered, the Parliament soon after meeting, were sooth'd up by the Lord Keeper <hi>Bridgman,</hi> under pretence of Great Advantages, to give the King in three Bills, no less than two Millions and a half, as it were to fix the Triple League with a Triple Supply. But the Parliament having given the Money, and consequently being prorogued, all Applications to forreign Ministers to enter into the Warrants of the Peace of <hi>Aix la Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> clear'd, and those that desired to be admitted were refused, insomuch that the Emperor himself was turned off with idle Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuses and blind Reasons. Upon which, followed a second War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> treacherously began by <hi>H.</hi> according to his Instructions from Court, at a time when the <hi>Dutch</hi> least sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected any such Thing, as relying upon the Faith of their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Alliances with Us; and as unfortunately carried on to the Loss of the <hi>English;</hi> not so much through the Cowardise of the Commanders, as by our unlucky Conjunction with the <hi>French,</hi> whose Business it was not to do us any Good, but to see
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109707:25"/> us batter one another, to found our Seas, to spy out Ports, to learn our Building, and contemplate our manner of Fighting, to consume ours, and preserve his own, Navy.</p>
            <p>However, the King having wasted all those vast Sums, which had been already given him, of which, there appeared, to the discerning part of the Kingdom, but a very bad account to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, wanted a new Supply, and then the Parliament, who were seldom summoned for any other Purpose, had leave to sit again; and in exchange of a Bill against the Papists, voted him one Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion two hundred and fifty thousand Pounds. So easily was the King induced to exhaust and squander away the Treasure of his Protestant Subjects, and to make them pay for their own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed Destruction, and supply those with continual Sums of Money, who had undertaken for the Change of their Religion and Government.</p>
            <p>Had it been twice as much more, it would have gone all the same way as the other had done, in Expenses of Pleasure and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Services; for the Sea-men were fed with a Bit and a Knock. But by this time the <hi>French</hi> having raised the Indignation of the <hi>English,</hi> by their ill Behaviour at Sea in all the Engagements, and perceiving their pernicious Counsels tended to nothing else, but by frequent Levies of Men and Money, to exhaust and weaken the Kingdom, and by their Conjunction with us, to raise a rational Jealosie of Poperty and <hi>French</hi> Government, till it should insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly devolve into both, by inclination or necessity; began to be for an honorable Peace with the States, which when it could be no longer resisted, was concluded.</p>
            <p>And thus was the <hi>French</hi> King, who made all his Wars, as he wrote to the Pope, for the Extirpation of Heresie, and a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Enemy of the <hi>English</hi> Protestants, not only assisted by the Councils of the Defender of the <hi>English</hi> Protestant Faith, but also with his Forces and his Arms, as appeared by his numerous Complements of <hi>English, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Irish,</hi> always in the <hi>French</hi> Army, as often as need required, still recruited and re-inforced, and by their Valour, as often prejudicial to the Allies of the King of <hi>England,</hi> against whom they were to fight, though he at the same time in Peace with them. Besides that, the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land's</hi> Magazines were dayly emptied to furnish the <hi>French</hi> with all sorts of Ammunition; of which, the following NOte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109707:26"/> but a small parcel, in comparison of what was dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed away, under colour of Cockets for <hi>Jersey.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Lead Shot, 21 Tuns.</item>
               <item>Gun-powder 7134 Barrels.</item>
               <item>Iron Shot, 18 Tun.</item>
               <item>Match, 88 Tun.</item>
               <item>Iron Ordnance, 441.</item>
               <item>Carriages, Bandeliers, Pikes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> proportionable.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Granadoes without number, shipt off under the colour of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rought Iron.</p>
            <p>And thus was the <hi>French</hi> King gratified for undoing the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Sea, by contributing all the King could wrap and rend of Men and Ammunition at Land, to make the Kingdoms, and the Protestant Religion's Enemy more potent and formidable in his Enterprizes against both.</p>
            <p>Nor will Story forget the frequent Prorogations of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this Reign. And indeed the Parliament was never summoned to sit, but when the Court wanted new Supplies for what had been extravangantly spent, and when they began to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the Miscarriages of the Government always dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missed.</p>
            <p>More particularly remarkable was one Prorogation, from the <hi>22d.</hi> of <hi>November</hi> 75. to the <hi>15th.</hi> of <hi>February</hi> 76. and then hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it after Dismission: there being no Record of any such thing done since the being of Parliaments in <hi>England,</hi> and the whole Reason of the Law, as well as the Practice and Custom of holding Parliaments being quite against it.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> for arguing by all the Laws of Parliament, and with great strength of Reason, that the Prorogation was null, and consequently, that the Parliament was dissolved, and the Earls of <hi>Salisbury</hi> and <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> for upholding the same Argument, were sent to the Tower, under the Notion of Contempt. And thus a Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation without President, was warranted by a President without Example.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:109707:26"/>
            <p>Neither will Story forget the Coming of the Duke of <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qus,</hi> the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Barillon</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> and their attending the King at <hi>New-Market,</hi> and so to <hi>London,</hi> and their being sent away again just upon the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being ready to sit again. The Matters that passed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>French</hi> Lords and the King, were, as it was said, for a Confirmation of continuing the Kings Subjects in the Service of <hi>France:</hi> An Abolition of all Claims and Demands from the Subjects of <hi>France,</hi> upon account of all Prizes made of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish,</hi> from the Year 74. and for the future from that Day. And a Demand of a farther Supply of <hi>French</hi> Money. However it were, so soon as the <hi>French</hi> Lords were departed the Land, and not before the Parliament met. And the first Message from the Court was for six hundred thousand pounds, for that the King could neither speak nor act without it, as the Secretary then declared. But the Commons insisting that an Alliance might be made with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and that the King would recall his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects out of the <hi>French</hi> Service, were not only checkt by the King, but put off by three Adjournals, contrary to the Usage of Parliaments, to the end the <hi>French</hi> King might have the more leisure to compleat his Design upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> before the Grand Council of the Nation should have the Opportunity of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing their Advice with the King to prevent it.</p>
            <p>Nor will Story forget, how that upon the Discovery of a Horrid Plot, even against the Person of the King himself, and for the Subversion of the Protestant Religion, and established Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Nation, and that the King well knew by <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Letters, and other significant Evidence, how deeply his Brother and the <hi>French</hi> King were combined therein, yet he sate down patiently, suffered the Discoverers of the Plot to be discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and discountenanced, and the Plot it self to be cry'd down and ridicul'd for an Imposture, while Sham-plots were set up by the Conspirators themselves, to cut off the most powerful Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers of the King of <hi>France's</hi> Designs and the Popish Interests.</p>
            <p>By all which Transactions it is apparent, that the whole Reign of this Prince was only a Combination of two great Monarchs, to reduce the <hi>English</hi> Dominions under the Slavery of <hi>France,</hi> and Jurisdiction of the Spiritual Tyranny of <hi>Rome;</hi> or at least, to make it more easie for a Popish Successor.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:109707:27"/>
            <p>For to what other Design else could tend the setting up a stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army, contrary to the Fundamental Constitutions of the Kingdom; the abandonning of a Nephew in <hi>Holland</hi> for so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, in Compliance with the <hi>French</hi> Designs upon <hi>Flanders</hi> and the United Provinces; the suffering of <hi>French</hi> Depredations and Cruelties exercised at Sea upon the <hi>English,</hi> to the spoiling the Trade, and impoverishing the Wealth of the Nation, the patiently brooking the Treacheries and Insolencies of the <hi>French,</hi> more especially relating to the Kings Affairs. The taking away of the Charters of all the Cities and Towns in the Kingdom, to frustrate the due Elections of Parliament Men. The counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing the Irregularities and unjust Proceedings of the Courts of <hi>Westminster.</hi> And lastly, the diligent Search all over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for Men of Arbitrary Principles, in order to promote them to publick Commissions and Imployments, but disgracing and displacing such as durst in such an universal Depravation, be faithful to their Trusts, which caused a Defection of several con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Persons, both Male and Female, to the Popish Religion, though more for their Temporal Safety, than in order to their Salvation.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Charles</hi> the Father is gone to his Place, and so is <hi>Charles</hi> the Son. And as for the Brother <hi>James</hi> the Second, he has withdrawn himself into <hi>France,</hi> after a short, but violent Reign, according to the Maxim of <hi>Nullum Violentum est Diuturnum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, when he stept into the Throne, he thought himself pretty sure, as well he might, having in his Brothers time got all the Keys, the strong Holds of the Kingdom, and the Navy into his Hands, besides a considerable standing Army, which he often exercised upon <hi>Hounslow-Heath,</hi> to terrifie the Nation. He had taken away all the Charters of all the Cities and Towns Corporate of the Nation, to have both them, and any Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he should call, to do his own and the Popes Business. However, notwithstanding all these Advantages, he thought it his most proper way to enter like a Lamb, rather than like a Wolf. And to that purpose he publishes a Declaration, where he solemnly promised not to invade the Properties of any one of his Subjects, and to protect the Professors of the established Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the peaceful Exercise of their Divine Worship, and the unmolested Enjoyment of their Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109707:27"/> and Temporal Rights. Yet in compliance with that grand Popish Maxim, <hi>That there is no Faith to be kept with Hereticks,</hi> no sooner did he feel himself warm in his Seat, but he erected an Arbitrary Ecclesiastical Court, to inquire into all Offences of Ecclesiastical Persons, from the Highest to the Lowest; and that their Commission might be effectual, they had an unlimitted Power to call Offences whatever they deemed to be so. It being therefore an Offence for the Bishop of <hi>London,</hi> upon the Kings Letter, not to silence Doctor <hi>Sharp,</hi> for uttering certain Expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in a Sermon, which displeased the Court, this Court there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fell upon him, and suspended him from the Exercise of his Episcopal Function.</p>
            <p>And because they might not want a share to intangle the whole Clergy of the Nation, a Declaration was put forth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be read in all the Churches and Chappels throughout the Kingdom, for the Repeal of the Test and Penal Laws against Papists, which they that refused to read, were liable to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure and Sentence of this same new erected Arbitrary Court.</p>
            <p>It was expected that the Bishops should have been the first to promote the distributing and publishing this Declaration in their several Diocesses. But instead of so doing, the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and six Suffragan Bishops presented their Answer in an humble and short Petition, That in regard his Majesties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for their distributing and publishing his Declaration for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conscience, was grounded upon a Dispensing Power, declared illegal by several Acts of Parliament, they humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sought his Majesty not to insist upon it. For which, the Arch-Bishop, and six more Bishops were committed to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and afterwards arraigned at the Kings-Bench-Bar, to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Infamy of the Prosecutors. And thus far the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was broke, in reference to the maintaining the Rights of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> In the next place, because the Fellows of <hi>Magdalen Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi> refused a <hi>Mandamus</hi> for admitting a Papist into their Society, all the Fellows of that House were not only outed of their Properties as Fellows of that Colledge, but so severely used, as to be denied all means of Subsistence and getting daily Bread. And this was an Invasion upon the Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Possessions of the Subject, contrary to the solemn Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the forementioned Declaration.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:109707:28"/>
            <p>And because the King was afraid, that, growing into years, he might not live to compleat the great Work he had begun, the next Attempt was to pretend an Heir of the Queens Body; and by a borrow'd Impostor, to have defeated the right Heir to the Crown.</p>
            <p>By which indirect Proceedings, the King had so alienated the Affections of his People from him, that when his Highness the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> came in to the Re-save of this distressed Nation, the King found himself so generally deserted by his People, that he lookt upon it as his best way to withdraw himself out of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Since then we have given our Thanks to Heaven forth is happy Deliverance from Popery and Slavery, it behoves us to be the more careful, that we may not be said to dally with Divine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, how we involve our selves again in those fatal Interests, that were so near the procuring our Destruction.</p>
            <p>Thus expired the unfortunate Reign of <hi>James</hi> the Second, a Misfortune incident to the Second of a Name in <hi>England;</hi> after he had sway'd the Scepter the best part of four years; and it is credibly reported, that to excuse the Miscarriages of his short Government, he should declare to some that followed him, that he had been ruined by a furious Woman, and a hot headed Fool. A certain Testimony from his own Lips, that he was not a Person of that Resolution which his Flatterers extoll'd him to be.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:109707:28"/>
            <head>A POLITICAL CATECHISM: Serving to instruct those that have made the Protestation concerning the Power and Priviledges of Parliament; taken out of his Majesties Answer to the Nineteen Propositions.</head>
            <p n="1">QUESTION I.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HOW many simple kinds are there of Civil Government of States and Common wealths?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Answer. <hi>There are thrée kinds of Government among Men; Absolute Monarchy, Aristocracy and Democracy,</hi> page 17.</p>
            <p n="2">Qu. 2. <hi>Are there any of these simple Forms perfect?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ans. <hi>All these have their particular Conveniences and Inconveniences,</hi> page 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Experience hath taught Men every where to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this, and accordingly there never was long (if at all) continued any of these Forms exactly simple; though some have more seemed such than others. Also in all Mixtures there is commonly some one of these Forms more conspicuous than the rest, from whence such a particular Government hath its Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
            <p n="3">Q. 3. <hi>Is the State of</hi> England <hi>governed by any one of these kinds simply?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:109707:29"/>
            <p>A. <hi>The Experience and Wisdom of your Ancestors hath moulded this [Government] out of a mixture of these,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <p n="4">Q. 4. <hi>What kind of Government then is that of the State of</hi> England?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>Regulated Monarchy,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. If this Government be a Mixture of all these, and a Regulated Monarchy; then it is a fond thing with us to talk of an Absolute Monarchy, and what an Absolute Monarchy is, or may do. And it is only the Language of Flattery that holds such Discourses.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. It needs not be accounted a Solecism (as some would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade us) to speak of free Subjects in a Monarchy, such a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy as ours is.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. If this Government be a Mixture of all three, then the House of Commons, the Representative Body of the People, must needs be allowed a share in Government (some at least) which yet is denied, <hi>Page</hi> 19.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="4">4. If this Government be a Mixture, then is not the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to these Laws, solely trusted to the King, as seems to be affirmed, <hi>Page</hi> 18.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="5">5. If the Government be regulated, why do Men tell us that the King is above all Law? for it is by Laws that he is regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="6">6. If the King be regulated by the Law, then is the King ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to the Law, and not to God only, as Men would make us believe.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="7">7. If the Monarchy or Regal Authority it self be regulated, then whatsoever is done by the King, undeniably without, and beyond the Limits of that Regulation, is not <hi>Regal Authority.</hi> And therefore</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="8">8. To resist the notorious Transgressions of that Regulation, is no resisting of <hi>Regal Authority.</hi> And</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="9">9. It is so far from being a Resisting of the Ordinance of God, that it is not so much as Resisting the Ordinance of Man.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="5">Q. 5. <hi>By whom was this Government framed in this sort? or who is to be accounted the immediate Efficient of the Constitution thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:109707:29"/>
            <p>A. <hi>The Experience und Wisdom of your Ancestors hath so moulded this,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. If our Ancestors were the Moulders of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then the King hath not his Power, solely or immediately, by Divine Right.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. Much less hath he his Power or Authority by Right of Conquest.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. But the immediate Original of it was from the People. And if so, Then—</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="4">4. In questioned Cases, the King is to produce his Grant (for he hath no more than what was granted) and not the People to shew a Reservation; for all is presumed to be reserved, which cannot be proved to be granted away.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="6">Q. 6. <hi>Is this regulated and mixt Monarchy as good as an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Monarchy, or better, or worse?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>This excellent Constitution of this Kingdom (the Ancient, Equal, Happy, Well-poised, and never enough commended Constitution of the Government of this Kingdom,</hi> page 17.) <hi>hath made this Nation so many years both Famous and Happy, and to a great Degrée of Envy,</hi> page 20.</p>
            <p n="7">Q. 7. <hi>How comes it to pass that this Constitution is so excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Experience and Wisdom of your Ancestors hath so moulded this, out of a Mixture of these, as to give to this Kingdom (as far as Humane Prudence can provide) the Conveniences of all thrée, without the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of any one,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observe.</hi> 1. Then those that would place in the King an Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and Arbitrary Power to do what he list, are destructive to the Nations Happiness, and Enemies to the Kingdom.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. If this Mixture cause this Happiness, then it is not the Greatness of the Kings Power over his People, but the Restraint of that Power that hath made this Kingdom Famous and Hapyy, for other Kings have Power as large, but not so much restrained; which largness of their Power, hath raised those Kings indeed, (but not their Kingdoms) to a great degree of Envy.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. Hence we discern, that it is possible for Kings to envy their Peoples Happiness, because the largeness of the Peoples Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109707:30"/> depends much upon the Restraint of the Kings Exorbitant Power.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="4">4. If this Mixture and well▪ poised Constitution have raised this Kingdom to so great a Degree of Envy, no marvel if Jesuitical Councils be active to overthrow this happy Constitution.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="8">Q. 8. <hi>What is the Conveniency or Good of Monarchy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The uniting of a Nation under one Head, to resist Invasion from abroad, and Insurrection at home,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. What pernicious Counsellors are they then to a Monarch, that advise him to bring in from abroad <hi>German</hi> Horse, or an <hi>Irish</hi> Army, or a Fleet of <hi>Danes</hi> to invade this Kingdom; or to imploy <hi>Dunkirk</hi> Ships to seize upon his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, which is so formally contrary to the proper Good or End of Monarchy it self?</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. Or are they better or worse that advise him to Authorize, or even permit any in his Name to Plunder, Rob, Spoil or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prison any of his Subjects, whom they have found peaceably in their Houses, or at work in the Fields, and have not disobeyed any legal Command o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his?</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="9">Q. 9. <hi>What is the Ill of Absolute Monarchy? or the Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to which it is liable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Ill of Absolute Monarchy, is Tyranny,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Therefore the more Absolute a Monarch is, the more prone to be a Tyrant.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. Therefore also it is safer to restrain the King of some Power to do us good, than to grant him too much opportunity to do us hurt; and the Danger is greater to the People in enlarging the Kings Power, then in restraining it somewhat.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="10">Q. 10. <hi>What is the Good or Conveniency of Aristocracy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The good of Aristocracy is the Conjunction of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils in the ablest Persons of a State for publick Benefit,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Then surely it is for the <hi>Publick Benefit</hi> of the State that this <hi>Conjunction of Councils</hi> in Parliament should be made use of more than once in thirteen or fourteen years; and the Law for a Triennial Parliament (if there were not others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the holding of a Parliament yearly) was a most necessary Law, as also that it should not be dissolved for fifty days.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:109707:30"/>2. It was not then intended in the <hi>Constitution of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that the King in the greatest Matters of Importance for publick Benefit, should only hear what they say, and then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, or reject it meerly at his own <hi>Pleasure;</hi> for this may be as well done in an Absolute Monarchy.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. Neither is it agreeable to the <hi>Constitution</hi> of this Kingdom, to withdraw the King from affording his Presence to his great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of State, that so the private Counsels of private Men may be preferred before those whom the Law and the <hi>Constitution of the Kingdom,</hi> counts the ablest to judge of Publick Benefit.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="11">Q. 11. <hi>What is the Ill of Aristocracy, or the Inconvenience to which it is liable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The ill of Aristocracy is Faction and Division,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Observ.</hi> What shall we say then to those private Counsellors that have abused the King, by perswading him first to withdraw himself from his Parliament, and then to call away the Members of both Houses, when yet without the Consent of both Houses, this Parliament cannot be adjourned to another place, much less dissolved? Yet if all would have come away at call, had it not been dissolved for want of legal Numbers remaining? And what greater Faction or Division can there be, than such as divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King and Parliament, and between the House and their Members? Are not they most pernicious Instruments, that make Monarchy it self (whose end is to unite, as was said before) thus far Guilty of <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Division?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">Q. 12. <hi>What is the Good or Conveniency of Democracy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The good of Democracy is Liberty, and the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Industry which Liberty begets,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Then the more Liberties are encroached upon, the more the People will be rendred cowardly and poor, as may be plain enough seen by comparing the Valour and Riches of this Nation in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> days, with what hath been of late Days.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. The King himself, when once his Subjects, by having lost their Liberties, shall lose withal their Courages, will prove the greatest Looser; for then his Kingdom will be an easie Prey to any Foreign Invader, or even to a Home-bred Usurper, that could gather any sudden Strength, and would promise more Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:109707:31"/>Q. 13. <hi>What is the Ill of Democracy, or the Inconvenience to which it is liable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Ills of Democracy, are Tumults, Violence and Licentiousness,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Observ.</hi> If these be the Evils for which the Peoples Liberty ought to be restrained by the Mixture in this Government, then the Restraint of the Liberty should be measured according to the Exigency of these Evils, and so much Liberty need only be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained, as is sufficient for the Prevention of these Evils.</p>
            <p n="14">Q. 14. <hi>What is the Mixture of this Kingdom, which gives it the Conveniences of all the three forementioned kinds of Government, without the Inconveniences of any one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>In this Kingdom the Laws are joyntly made by a King, by a House of Péers, and by a House of Commons chosen by the People: All having frée Votes, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular priviledges,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Whereas there hath been great question made by many what is meant by the Power and Priviledges of Parliament, mentioned in the Protestation, which hath been so generally made throughout the Kingdom: There is no reason to doubt but those things which the King grants afterward, to be the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Priviledge of each House, and of both, are their certain Priviledges according to Law, and the Constitution of the Kingdom; and to the maintaining of them, every one that hath made the Protestation is most strictly bound, without peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or shift.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Priviledges which the King challenges to himself, are to be yielded to, only so far forth as they are consistent with the acknowledged Priviledges of the two Houses; because the Monarchy being acknowledged to be a regulated Monarchy, and the Government mixt of Aristocracy and Democracy, as well as Monarchy; it is the Priviledges of the two Houses of Parliament that makes the Mixture, and so they must regulate and interpret the Priviledges of the King, and not the Priviledges of the King regulate or interpret theirs, save only to the maintaining still the Regal Dignity, and the Succession according to Laws.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="15">Q. 15. <hi>What Priviledges doth the King challenge to himself?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Government according to these Laws, is trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the King Power of Treaties of War and Peace,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109707:31"/> of making Péers, of choosing Officers, and Councellors for State, Iudges for Law, Commanders for Forts and Castles; giving Commissions for raisig Men to make War abroad, or to prevent or provide against Invasions and Insurrections at home, Benefit of Confiscations, Power of Pardoning, and some other of like kind are placed in the King,</hi> page 18.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. That all these are ordinarily in the King, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Custom teaches, even those that know not the Law, by reading, but by what hath been noted before, and follows after, it is to be understood only so, as not to prejudice the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Houses of Parliament, especially in Cases of Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity (of which hereafter.) Also—</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. It is acknowledged here, that the Government, Trusted, is to be according to the Laws, and so all these things are not abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely in the King; as for instance, <hi>Pardons,</hi> the Law denies Power of Pardoning wilful Murther; and Benefit of some Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscations belongs to some private Lords of Mannors.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. If Government only according to Law be trusted to the King, then to resist notorious illegal Violences is not to resist the Kings Authority.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="16">Q. 16. <hi>For what end is this Authority trusted to the King, and placed in him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>For our Subjects sake these Rights are invested in us,</hi> page 17. <hi>The Prince may not make use of this high and perpetual Power to the Hurt of those for whose Good he hath it,</hi> page 19.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Then the Good of the Subjects is ever to be preferred before the Monarchical Greatness of the King (the End is ever more considerable than the Means) <hi>Salus Populi is Suprema Lex.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. Whosoever counsels the King to any thing against the Good of his Subjects, is the Kings Enemy as well as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, by attempting to turn him from that which is the end of his Authority.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="17">Q. 17. <hi>To what purpose especially are the Priviledges of the House of Commons and the House of Peers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>That the Prince may not make use of his high and perpetual Power to the Hurt of those, for whose Good he hath it; and make use of the Name of publick Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109707:32"/> for the Gain of his private Favorites and Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> &amp;c. page 19.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. The Law then supposes, that such Cases may fall out, though it then charge the Blame upon those <hi>Favorites</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> and not upon the King (as we shall see by and by.)</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. We need not wonder then why private <hi>Favorites</hi> and <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers</hi> are such Enemies to Parliaments and their Priviledges, which are on purpose to hinder their Gains: Of which also more anon.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. The two Houses are by the Law it seems, to be <hi>Trusted,</hi> when they declare that the Power is made use of for the Hurt of the People; and the Name of <hi>Publick Necessity</hi> made use of for the Gain of <hi>Private Favorites</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> and the like.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="18">Q. 18. <hi>What are the special Priviledges of the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons towards this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The House of Commons, an excellent Conserver of Liberty—is solely intrusted with the first Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning the Levies of Moneys, which is the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news as well of Peace as of War,</hi> &amp;c. page 19.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. It seems then the <hi>House of Commons</hi> is presumed to be more careful for the Subjects Liberties, than either the King, or the House of Peers.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. Then it must needs be strange for any to conceive (as the Kings Declarations would perswade) that the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons would fight against and subvert the Liberty and Property of the Subject, and the Kings Favorites and Followers fight for them, and protect them.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. Then no Moneys may be levied, neither for Peace nor War, no, not under pretence of <hi>Publick Necessity</hi> (as Ship Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Monopolies were) without the House of Commons first propound and grant it.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="4">4. If the House of Commons be an <hi>excellent Conserver of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> it must needs have some power in some cases to levy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, even without the Kings Consent; or else it will be utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to conserve <hi>Liberty</hi> at all. Of which likewise more anon.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="19">Q. 19. <hi>But if the Kings private Favorites and Followers have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually perswaded him to any thing against the Laws and Liberties of the Subject, with what further Power and Priviledge is the House of Commons intrusted toward the Conserving of Liberty?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:109707:32"/>
            <p>A. <hi>With the impeaching of those, who for their own ends, though countenanced by any surreptitiously gotten Command of the King, have violated that Law, which he is bound (when he knows it) to protect; and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of which, they were bound to advise him, at least not to serve him in the contrary,</hi> page 19.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Then it is no Excuse to any that violate the Laws, that they <hi>serve the King</hi> in it.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. The Law counts all Commands from the King, which are any way contrary to the Law, <hi>Surreptitiously gotten.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. Then the Parliament speaks according to the Law, when they constantly lay the Blame of all Violations upon the Kings <hi>Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> and their getting surreptitiously Commands from him, and not upon the King himself.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="4">4. No Command of the King is to hinder the Commons from impeaching such as have violated the Law.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="5">5. The King is bound not to protect any of his Followers and Favorites against the Commons Impeachment of them; because he knows and affirms, that he is bound to protect the Laws, and that this is the Law, that the Commons are to impeach such.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="20">Q. 20. <hi>What is the special Priviledge of the House of Peers in the former Case of such Favorites and Followers of the Kings, as are impeached by the Commons? and so to decide all Matters in Questions between the King and People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Lords being trusted with a Iudicatory Power, are an excellent Scréen and Bank betwéen the Prince and the People, to assist each against any Encroachment of the other, and by just Iudgments, to preserve that Law which ought to be the Rule of every one of the thrée,</hi> page 19.</p>
            <p n="21">Q. 21. <hi>But have the two Houses Power to put their Judgments into Execution, as well as to Impeach and Judge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The power of punishment is already in your Hands, according to Law,</hi> page 20.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Then again, it is no wonder that the Kings <hi>Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites</hi> and <hi>Followers</hi> hate Parliaments, (who not only hinder their Gain, but have power to punish them) when they have violated the Laws.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:109707:33"/>2. Then the Lords (and much more the two Houses together) are Supream Judges of all Matters in difference between the King, and the People, and have power to prevent all the Kings En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments upon the People,, as well as the Peoples upon him.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. Then the King is bound not to protect any, whom the Lords, upon the Impeachment of the Commons, have judged Delinquents; for he hath granted that he is bound to protect the Law, and that according to Law, the Power of Punishing (even of his <hi>Favorites</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> fore-spoken of) is in their Hands, and they cannot punish them, so long as he protects them.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="4">4. Then the Law allows them as the Supream Judicatory (even that which must be a Skreen between the King and the People, and assist the People against the Kings Encroachments, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the Kings <hi>Favorites</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> though countenanced by Surreptitiously-gotten Commands from the King) a power to bring such as they have judged (or are to judge) to condign Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, which is granted to all inferior Judges in their Circuits and Jurisdictions.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="5">5. Then if those Delinquents get the King to protect them, or surreptitiously get Commands of him, to raise Arms to shelter themselves against the Judgment of the two Houses; the two Houses have power by the Law, to raise not only the <hi>Posse Comita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> of those Counties where such Delinquents are, to apprehend them, but also the <hi>Posse Regni,</hi> the Power of the whole Kingdom, if need be; or else the Power of Punishment is not in their hands according to Law, and it would be safer contemning and scorning and opposing the highest Judicatory, the Parliament, than any inferior Court, a Judge of Assize, or the like; and they that could get Commands to violate the Law before, would easily get protection against the Parliament, when they are questioned, if the Parliament had no Power to raise Arms to suppress them.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="22">Q. 22. <hi>But if there be an Attempt or Danger, that the Kings Favorites and Followers go about to change this Regulated Monarchy into an Arbitrary Government, and so into a Tiranny; is there Authority in the Houses sufficient, according to what was fore menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, to remedy this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Power legally placed in both Houses, is more than sufficient to prevent and restrain the power of Tiranny,</hi> page 20.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:109707:33"/>
                     <hi>Observ.</hi> 1. Then at least whatever power is necessary to prevent or restrain the power of Tiranny, is confessed to be legally pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in both Houses; for else there is not Power sufficient, much less, more than sufficient.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="2">2. Then it is lawful for the two Houses to raise Arms to defend themselves, in case an Army be raised aginst them, for else they have not power sufficient to restrain the power of Tiranny. There is no greater Attempt of Tiranny than to raise Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Houses of Parliament, and there is no way to restrain this Tiranny, but by raising Arms in their own Defence. Less than this cannot be sufficient.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="3">3. If a Legal Power be placed in them, not only to restrain, but <hi>prevent the Power of Tiranny,</hi> then they are the Legal Judges, when there is danger of Tiranny; and they have Legal Power to Command their Judgment to be obeyed, for prevention as well as restraint of <hi>Tiranny.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="4">4. Then it is lawful for them to provide for their own and the Kingdoms Safety, and they have legal power to command the People to this purpose, not only when Arms are actually raised against them, but when they discern, and accordingly declare a Preparation made towards it: for if they let alone altogether the <hi>Exercise</hi> of their Power, till Arms are actually raised against them, they may in all likelyhood find it too late, not only to <hi>Prevent,</hi> but even to <hi>Restrain the Power of Tiranny.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="5">5, Then they have legal power in such times of Danger, to put into safe hands, such Forts, Ports, Magazines, Ships, and Power of the <hi>Militia,</hi> as are intended, or likely to be intended, to introduce a Tiranny; for else they cannot have Power suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to <hi>Prevent</hi> or <hi>Restrain the Power of Tiranny.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="6">6. Then they have legal Power to levy Moneys, Arms, Horse, Ammunitions, upon the Subjects, in such Cases of <hi>Danger,</hi> even without or against the Kings Consent; for it cannot be imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that in such Cases, when the Kings Favorites and Followers have gotten Commands from him, to protect them in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquencies, and Attempts to introduce Tiranny, that ever he will consent to Levies of Monevs against those Favorites and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of his, or to the raising Arms against them, especially he being still in their Hands, and among them, and not with his Parliament; and without such Levies of Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109707:34"/> possible for the two Houses of Parliament to prevent or restrain sufficiently the <hi>Power of Tiranny.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="7">7. They that have made the <hi>Protestation,</hi> to maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>Power and Priviledges of Parliament,</hi> may see in all these things (acknowledged by the King, and clearly following from this Acknowledgments) what is that <hi>Power,</hi> and what are <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament,</hi> which they have so solemnly in the Presence of Almighty God, vowed, promised and protested to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p n="8">8. And finally, since the two Houses of <hi>Parliament</hi> have so often and fully declared their <hi>Intentions</hi> in setling the <hi>Militia,</hi> securing <hi>Hull</hi> and the Magazine there, and the Navy at Sea, with the Ports and Forts, and afterward in raising Arms under the Command of the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> and last of all, levying Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys by voluntary Contributions and Assessments; they have only used that <hi>Legal Power</hi> which is in them for the <hi>Punishment</hi> of <hi>Delinquents,</hi> and for the <hi>Prevention</hi> and <hi>Restraint</hi> of the <hi>Power of Tiranny,</hi> of all which they are the Legal Judges; and all the Subjects of this Kingdom are bound by the Laws to obey them herein, and those doubly bound that have made the late <hi>Protestation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="transcription">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:109707:34"/>
            <head>That the Reader may the better discern how the Answers here applied do agree with the Words of His Majesties Answer to the Nineteen Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, I have here transcribed so much of it as concerns this Particular.</head>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 17.</hi> WE call God to witness, that as for our Subjects Sake these Rights are vested in Us, so for their Sakes (as well as for our own) we are resolved not to quit them, nor to subvert though in a Parliamentary way the ancient, equal, happy, wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poised, and never-enough commended Constitution of the Government of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>There being thrée kinds of Government amongst Men, Absolute Monarchy, Aristocracy, and Democracy, and all these having their Particular Conveniences and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 18.</hi> The Experience and Wisdom of your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors hath so moulded this out of a Mixture of these, as to give to this Kingdom as far as humane Prudence can provide) the Conveniences of all thrée, without the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences of any one, as long as the Ballance hangs even betwéen the thrée Estates, and they run joyntly on in their proper Channel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e getting Verdure and Fertility in the Meadows on both sides) and the overflowing of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on either side, raise no Deluge or Inundation. The Ill of Adsolute Monarchy is Tiranny: The ill of Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy is Faction and Division: The Ills of Democracy are Tumults, Violence, and Licentiousness. The Good of Monarchy is the uniting a Nation under one Head, to resist Invasion from abroad, and Insurrection at Home: The Good of Aristocracy, is the Conjunction of Councel
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109707:35"/> in the ablest Persons of a State for the publick Benefit: The Good of Democracy, is Liberty, and the Courage and Industry which Liberty begets.</p>
               <p>In this Kingdom the Laws are joyntly made by a King, by a House of Péers, and by a House of Commons chosen by the People, all having frée Votes and particular Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges. The Government, according to these Laws, is trusted to the King, Power of Treaties of War and Peace, of making Péers, of choosing Officers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellors for State, Iudges for Law, Commanders for Forts and Castles, giving Commissions for raising Men to make War abroad, or to prevent and provide against Invasions or Insurrections at home, Benefit of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscations, Power of Pardoning, and some more of the like kind are placed in the King—Again, <hi>Pag. 19.</hi> That the Prince may not make use of this high and perpetual Power to the Hurt of those for whose Good he hath it, and make use of the Name of Public Necessity for the Gain of his private Favorites and Followers to the Detriment of his People; the House of Commons, an excellent Conserver of Liberty, but never intended for any share in Government, or the chusing of them that should govern) is solely intrusted with the first Propositions concerning the Levies of Moneys (which is the Sinews as well of Peace as War) and the impeaching of those, who for their own Ends, though countenanced by any surreptiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously gotten Command of the King, have violated that Law, which he is bound (when he knows it to protect, and to the Protection of which they were bound to advise him, at least not to serve him to the contrary: and the Lords being trusted with a Iudicatory Power, are an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessent Scréen and Bank betwéen the Prince and People, to assist each against any Incroachments of the other, and by just Iudgments to preserve that Law which ought to be the Rule of every one of the thrée—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 20.</hi> Since therefore the Power legally placed in both Houses is more than sufficient to prevent and restrain the Power of Tiranny:—since this would be a total Subversign of the Fundamental Laws, and that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109707:35"/> Constitution of this Kingdom, which hath made this Nation so many years both famous and happy, to a great degrée of Envy; ūce to the Power of PunisHing which is already in your Hands according to Law) if—since the Encroaching of one of these Estates upon the Power of the other is unhappy in the Effects both to them and all the rest—<hi>Pag. 22.</hi> Our Answer is, <hi>Nolumns Leges Angliae mutari.</hi> But this we promise, that we will be as careful of preserving the Laws in what is supposed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern wholly our Subjects, as in what most concerns Our self: For indéed We profess to believe that the Preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every Law concerns Us, those of Obedience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not secure, when those of Protection are violated.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>